He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and
to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and
unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, Scorpion and Serpent Stompers.
You are listening for Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen D'Yung is with me
from Lafayette Louisiana, and I'm from...
Get over here.
Thank you, sorry.
I heard Scorpion.
Wow, that's a blast for the past right there.
Please don't finish me.
Brutality. Yes. And anyway, I'm Father Andrew Manez. You know that. If you're
listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855-237-2346.
And Matyshka Trudy should be taking your calls and we will get to them in the
second part of our show. Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners and
also by Chrysostom Academy. A lot of you listeners out there work from home. We
If you know that, if you're telecommuting...
you could probably live almost anywhere you like.
If you're a parent of school age kids,
and you're like me working from a virtual office,
then one of your big considerations for where you live
is where your kids go to school.
I love living in the Lehigh Valley of Pennsylvania.
Part of why is because my kids go to Chrysostom Academy,
and it's a pan orthodox classical school
with elementary through high school students.
It is on a beautiful 55 acre wooded campus
with a creek running next to it.
It has the highest economic standards
and it is for
not just on educating the mind but forming the whole person in Christ.
So if you don't live here yet, think about moving to the Lehigh Valley
and sending your kids to Chrysostom Academy.
And even if you don't telecommute, our local economy is growing,
and it's producing jobs.
So maybe more of those could be for you.
We've got eight Orthodox parishes in our metro area.
You can visit Chrysostomacademy.org to see what I'm talking about.
Also.
You do have to be a little careful there, because I'll be the name.
Well, no, this time of year, the whole, you know,
peeps production is ramping up.
That's true.
So just be a little careful that you're not taking
an Easter-related peep temp job.
Yeah, they do make peeps that might not
stick around for you.
It's absolutely true.
We are the home of peeps.
Also, though, we are still selling tickets
for the Lord of Spirits Conference on October 26th through 29th,
20th, 23th, right now.
Only commuter tickets are available
because we have
sold out the lodging at the Antioch Invillage.
You may need X.
You can go to store.ancientfeath.com slash events
to get your ticket and there actually aren't
even that many left.
So get a move on.
You can like sleep at your car in the parking lot,
take kind of a sink bath.
There's bathrooms across from the dining hall.
Please don't do that.
Go goblin mode on the whole conference.
I just said, I just said someone could.
I just said, yeah, good.
Please don't just say that.
Yes, they could.
They could do a lot of things.
Right.
So Orthodox Christians around the world were collectively puzzled when it was announced
on social media recently that King Charles III of the United Kingdom and 14 other common
wealth realms, what was at his upcoming coronation going to be anointed with chrism that had
been blessed by the Orthodox Patriarch of Jerusalem.
and also the Anglican Arbespishop in the same city.
In between the hubbub and guessing games
over whether what happened was some kind of
consileration.
Some might have been startled to discover
that the word chrysum
turns out to be usable for any kind of anointing oil,
not just the kind used at baptism.
Does this mean that Charles is going to be anointing?
Did the Byzantine Emperor?
Yes.
We will leave that to the excitable to debate,
right after Father Stephen just gives away the answer.
No, sorry.
spoilers. Come on. It turns out though that we at the Lord of Spirits podcast were already
going to be talking about the making of kings. So thanks, King Charles, thanks patriarch
Theophilus and thanks Archbishop Hussam Naum for the alley-oop. So where does kingship
really originate anyway, Father Stephen? Is it divine right of kings? Is it prime minister?
should clarify right that there actually was not a
Concelebration. No, I-
didn't see any actual photos of a concentration. But people were well, there's actually video.
There's a video of the whole thing on the TikToks. Uh oh. So you just have to find a
zoomer to show you the TikToks. And you can see the whole thing.
I've been avoiding TikTok. Um, and, uh, yes. So as far as I could tell the, the
Anglican archbishop was primarily there to convey the blessed oil back to
Great Britain. That's nice to him. Yeah. So, and the reason for that also, by the way, is that Charles's father,
Pritz Philip, was part of the Greek royal family. Yeah, I mean, he was an Orthodox Christian,
although he became Anglican, of course, when he was, I think, sometime before he married,
and married required to by law.
By law.
Yeah, right.
You want to marry this particular person?
You have to become an advocate.
But Charles' grandmother though, she ended up her life
as an Orthodox nun.
So how about that?
Yes, yes.
And the olives were taken from, used for the oil,
were taken from a grove near where she's buried
on the Mount of Loves.
Very nice.
So that's why the patriarch of Jerusalem
was involved in all this.
And also technically Charles is also
a descendant of the Greek royal family on his father's side.
Because otherwise, no one's going to listen to what we say.
They're just going to be vexed by the panheracy of ecumenism.
And we'll be able to take in the knowledge that we're about to drop.
So also, I wanted to note, because I know our last episode was a little bit brain breaking.
that once we are done with our sacrament series.
which I mean, that could be a while, right?
We're at eight and counting.
But once we eventually are dealt with this agribusiness,
we are going to return to this topic of the soul.
So, hey, everybody.
Talk about what it means to become a spirit.
That's the teaser.
Oh, man.
I'm going to drop out there.
Let's go back to Kings.
Back to tonight's topic, which will invariably get the spirit
invariably get.
to in the third half or near there too.
We talked a little bit about the anointing of kings
in the episode in which we talked about
the concept of the Messiah,
which I'm sure we had a clever title too,
but I don't remember it.
Yes.
That's what Messiah means.
It means an anointed one.
The anointed one.
So we talked about,
And so within that, we talked about anointed.
But so tonight's episode where we're talking about one of the sacraments, one of the Holy
Mysteries, the Orthodox Church, which is the consecration of the Emperor, that's where
this is going.
We need to start by sort of revisiting obviously the right of the consecration of the Emperor
has its beginnings in the consecration of kings and in kingship itself. Right?
which begins the Old Testament.
And so if you're following your generic Lord of Spirits
episode planner, we're starting a Genesis 1.
Hey.
So, surprise, surprise, surprise.
Yes, everyone is shocked.
And technically we're starting a Genesis 2
versus 1 and 2, really.
That's true, because this is Sabbath stuff.
Sabbath stuff, right?
And so we've talked about this before on the show that,
and this is potentially rooting Sunday school,
that the way we tend to think of,
on the seventh day,
the Lord completed his work, and he rested.
We tend to think of that in terms of like,
wow, that was tough, making a holy universe in six days.
So now I'm gonna take a break.
And of course that's
not what's going on. God did not need a break, but when it refers to God resting, that is
him resting, meaning being seated upon the divine throne, to preside over now his creation,
which he has completed creating. And so this theme of kingship, of God is the king over
creation starts right there at the
echo. And so we talked, we've talked about before how the Sabbath then, the weekly Sabbath,
the Sabbath year, right? That the Sabbaths that were commanded in the Torah were for Israel
to participate, not in God taking a break, but to participate in the kingdom, right?
To participate in God's reign. That's why it was at the end of the week, right? Because
it was.
pointing forward to the coming of God's kingdom on Earth as it isn't heaven.
Right? So that kingship is established there. And the way in which the Torah itself,
and several significant portions of the Torah function are, and I know we've talked
about this before the show but
When you come back at it again from this angle is as a covenant documents
We talked about the Hebrew word is berate
The Greek word is deothicky
That often gets translated in English now as testament rather than as covenant and so
So a lot of folks have a bifurcation in their brain.
Where would you say Old Testament, New Testament, they think...
about divisions of the Bible, part one and part two of the Bible, when really that means
old covenant, new covenant, those are the same terms.
And so the old covenant, the original covenant is a covenant document and not just in general
but of a particular type.
When we hear covenant, we tend to think of like, oh, well, it's like a contract.
It's like an agreement, right?
If we hear the word testament, we think like,
oh, last will and testament, it's like a legal document.
But the actual pattern
in that we see in the Torah and in significant sections of it
is pattern after a particular type
of sort of treaty document from the ancient Near East.
and we found a bug.
of examples that match up really closely in Hittite documents. Well, these are written
in Lovian, but they're Hittite documents. They're what are called Suserente Treaties or
Suseran Vassal Treaties. They are a type of treaty document that was issued by a king to his
is vassals.
So this king is now.
So no lesser.
Right.
So this king is now.
take control of a number of cities.
He's like the Great King.
Those cities have their own rulers,
but now since he's in charge,
he can now give his terms to those rulers
who are now under his authority.
And the particular pattern in broad strokes,
we won't go too deeply into this right now tonight,
but in broad strokes,
The pattern is that those begin with an identification.
of the king, of the great king, and sort of historical recounting of who he is and what he's
done and particularly what he's done on behalf of the vassal. Then it outlines the vassal's
responsibilities, his duties to the great king. And then at the end, there is a section.
of here are all the good things that will happen if you do what you're supposed to do
and then here are all the bad things that will happen if you don't do what you're supposed to do.
And one of the really obvious places where you can see this pattern within the Torah
is in the Ten Commandments.
What we now call the Ten Commandments, which are in Exodus 20 and then again in Deuteronomy 5.
And those begin with
right? I am Yahweh your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt out of the house of slavery,
right? So here's who I am, here is what I have done for you. Now here are your responsibilities.
You love to know that God's before me you love make a graven image etc etc.
Right? It's less obvious that the ten commandments, right? The blessings of curses though there are a few
you listed in there.
that you honor your father and mother so that your days may be long in the land that Yahweh or God is giving you.
So there are some contained. But if you want to see a very full example of this pattern,
the entire Book of Deuteronomy follows this pattern.
The Book of Deuteronomy begins with a historical sort of prologue in the middle it has commandments
And...
And then it ends chapter 28 through 30 with a series of blessings, if those are kept and
curses if they are not.
Yeah.
Which we talk about that in some detail on the blessings in curses episode.
So, um, but so this is the pattern.
And so the very pattern within which God first reveals Himself to Israel here in the
Torah is following this pattern of presenting him as the great king.
Now that said, that said, we are so most of the folks who listen to this show, there are
a lot who don't, but the majority, the simple majority are in the United States.
Another big chunk are in the UK and Commonwealth countries, you know, the shows in English, so that
will tend to happen.
and we have a chug of-
Australians. Yes, we do. We have Australia. Yes, probably not. Yeah. Right. And so in all of these places,
the popular Christianity, as it were, is either Puritan or heavily influenced by Puritanism.
And puretonism is not overly fond of kings.
America is of course worse about this than the other place.
as I mentioned. Right. It's kind of our whole founding deal here in America. Yeah, we're
not quite as bad as the French, but it's kind of our race on debt. Yeah. And so that has colored
the way a lot of us have been taught the Old Testament, where it is very much presented as if
before a few chapters into the book of Samuel.
Israel was sort of ruled directly by God as king and that's how things should have stayed,
but man, those no good Israelites, they demanded a king from God and that was bad and he gave
him one.
And then, you know, David shows up and it's really good at it.
I don't know how that works into the narrative, but that's very clearly not true if we read
carefully.
because as we just ran
and the whole book of Deuteronomy is patterned in the form of this treaty from the Great King,
right? The references I'm making here are deliberate, let the listener understand. But Deuteronomy
contains within it, Deuteronomy 17 versus 14 through 20, which are explicitly commandments
aimed at the human king who is going to reign-
over Israel. Which there isn't one for a while yet. There wasn't one for a while yet. But so this
was not something unforeseen by God. They haven't entered the Promised Land yet, but this is kind of
on the Virgin. That's when Deuteronomy is delivered. The idea that there will be one particular
vessel that not only are all of the Israelites or the Israelites elders or the
profit or a judge are vast.
who are receiving the Torah, but that there is going to be one particular vassal king
who is going to have particular responsibilities above and beyond the responsibilities given
to other Israelites is right here in the middle of the statement of the old covenant.
Right. So that, of course, raises the question of what is going on then in, like, first
Samuel Ler, first king.
eight, right? And we talked about this at a previous episode a little bit, but just to
right repeat it. Here at least in summary, the problem wasn't that they wanted a king.
The problem is that they wanted a king like the other nations. Specifically. Yeah.
I was gonna say who's gonna lead him in a battle because like they weren't winning the way they wanted to.
And so that's like well we need to get one of those kings because look how
winning they are. Right. So they had just suffered this defeat where they said,
hey, we're going to go into battle just of their own decision. And we're going to
take the Ark of the covenant out in front of us. And then we'll win because we
have the Ark of the covenant. So God will make us win. Right. And of course,
that didn't work out so good for them and they lost the Ark and everything. But
rather than getting the message, they were supposed to get from that. The message
that got was well I guess we can't count on God
God to help.
Right?
Yeah.
So we,
I mean, there's one big themes in the scriptures
of like, you know, do it yourself.
That doesn't work out well.
You know, like I have my own plan,
I have my own ideas despite what God has said to do.
Just, yeah, yeah.
And this compounds it because this is,
I'm gonna go into business for myself
and then when it doesn't work out,
I'm gonna blame God.
Right?
That's,
so,
And so this is what's going on there.
This is why God says to Samuel, right, they haven't rejected you, they've rejected me, right?
This is the problem there, not that they were going to have a king, right, in general. But so
that passage in Deuteronomy, Deuteronomy 17, 14 through 20 sort of lays out, right here, the
particular commandments directed at the king. This is who the king over Israel is supposed to be
what he's supposed to be.
host to do and not do.
So I'm going to read this and it's it's not one verse.
It's a few verses.
So listen closely everybody.
Starting with verse 14, when you come to the land that the Lord your God is giving you
and you possess it and dwell in it and then say, I will set a king over me like
all the nations that are around me.
You may indeed set a king over you whom the l-
Lord your God will choose, one from among your brothers you shall set as king over you.
You may not put a foreigner over you who is not your brother.
Only he must not acquire many horses for himself or cause the people to return to Egypt in
order to acquire many horses, since the Lord has said to you, you shall never return that
way again.
And he shall not acquire many wives for himself, lest his heart turn away nor shall he
acquire for himself excessive silver and gold.
when he sits on the throne of his king
him, he shall write for himself in a book, a copy of this law, approved by the
Levitical Priests. And it shall be with him, and he shall read it in all the days of his life,
that he may learn to fear the Lord his God by keeping all the words of this law and these
statutes and doing them, that his heart may not be lifted up above his brothers, and that he may
not turn aside from the commandment either to the right hand or to the left, so that he may continue
long in his kingdom. He and his children.
in Israel. There's a few things there that are certainly different from the kings of the
nations. Yes. Yeah. Right. And so first of all, the king has to be an Israelite. They
can't decide like, hey, King of Moab seems to have it going on. Let's just become vassals
of his. Right. Yeah. And the
The thing about the horses, acquiring many horses, it's not just that like Kings collected
horses.
That's obviously both a mark of wealth, but primarily because it's going to talk about
silver and gold, this is military power.
Yeah.
Right.
They didn't have fighter jets.
They didn't have tanks.
They had horses that pulled chariots.
And so, uh, temptation to go...
back to Egypt to make some kind of deal, temptation to just in general build a large standing
army because what's that going to do?
Well, we've talked before about Deuteronomy and the laws regarding warfare.
They're not supposed to be committing offensive warfare.
Yeah, no conquering to increase their territory.
Yeah, they're not supposed to be trying to set up the Israelite Empire, right?
Which is, which take over the world.
Crazy
in ancient world's terms.
Like of course you would do that if you could.
Like that's what you could.
Yeah, oh yeah.
Everyone did.
Yeah.
There's no United Nations.
You know, Patrick Resolutions telling you please don't do that.
Or else we'll say please don't do that again.
Right.
And obviously acquiring many wives, right?
We know where that's going to go with Solomon
and even with David, frankly.
and trying to
to
obviously, Horde Great Wealth, right?
Rather, right, as opposed to all that.
So that's kind of a picture of what
the other nation's kings were doing.
Rather, he's supposed to make a copy of the Torah for himself.
Yeah.
Which means he needs to learn to read and write
in order to be able to study specifically the Torah.
Yep.
and that
approval by the Levites, right? It means that it's not just, again, he's not... Here's the
scriptures going to business for yourself, right? Where he could use it to justify whatever
he's going to do, and his rule and that kind of thing. But he's being guided by the priests.
He is under spiritual authority, even as he is the highest governmental authority underneath
God Himself.
Yeah, and they're probably checking to make sure that he actually copied it right. Yeah
You know like okay, and it says you know this law right so I
Mean that's a whole copy of the Torah. Yeah, yeah
and then and then that is because
the express purpose is that in
Learning the commandments in keeping the commands and following the way of life that's outlined in the Torah
His heart.
heart will not be lifted up above his brothers.
Again, different from the kings of the nations.
And so not only is he not to do these sort of material things
in terms of wealth, military power, wives, right?
But he has not to even in his heart, right?
Even even in his own thinking, think himself better.
than the other Israelites. He has this particular role, but he is not better. And this is especially
important when you consider that the kings of the neighboring nations, including Pharaoh back in
Egypt, were worshipped as gods. They most definitely were above the rest of the Egyptians.
Right. Pharaoh was a God. His
family, they were divine. That's why there was so much
intermarriage, shall we say, within the royal families and all of these city
states and in Egypt. Because you couldn't marry a commoner because they were just humans.
And so this is a dramatic departure from that. Right. So the king is not
sort of another class of being. He is not a higher being. No, it's not like...
the Sumerian Kings list where the kingship comes down from heaven.
Yeah, he's not a demigod, he's not a son of a god.
No, that's tough.
He is, well, son of god does become a royal title, but in a different sense.
Yeah.
And so he is essentially the eldest brother.
Right, the other Israelites are his brothers.
He is just sort of the eldest brother.
And so a lot of people will say
that Saint Paul, right, what what are the issues people have with Saint Paul is
that when you read the gospels especially the synoptic gospels, Christ is
constantly talking about the kingdom. There's all this kingdom language,
king language, right, and then people will say, well, Saint Paul doesn't use that
language. Right? And while you can make that case if you're just going by...
Greek words conceptually.
When St. Paul is using the language of Christ as first born
among many brethren, of Christ as the Son of God
and our adoption as sons and heirs of God, right?
This is appealing to the way in which
covenantal inheritance was understood.
The eldest brother inherits everything
and then distribute.
it to the other heirs. And so in the same sense, the king is functioning as this elder brother.
He has these particular responsibilities before God. He is sort of the vassal of vassals.
But he has an intermediary figure in the sense of having an added set of responsibilities
both toward God and toward his brothers.
not as being a special class of human, or more than human.
Right?
So, after Deuteronomy, you get Joshua, where Joshua sort of carries on Moses' role,
which is a sort of kingly role in the sense that Joshua is the one leading into...
battle Joshua is the one as Moses had,
who is in charge of the various judges and elders
of the people and that kind of thing.
But then you get into the book of Judges proper
and there is this refrain over and over again
that in that day there was no king
and everyone did what was right in their own eyes.
Yeah, yeah.
And this is not to say like, you know,
It was just beautiful and I kicked free.
them. Yes. And everything was guessed. Sorry, anarchists. It judges at least. That's not a good thing.
Right. That's everything's a mess. Right. And how is that working within the book of judges? Well,
we've talked before a lot about what justice is biblically. So justice, Mishpoth, right, is when
everything is in its proper place. Everything is related properly.
everything else and everything is functioning peacefully and appropriately in
in good order, right? That's justice. And so since we don't have someone doing
that, we don't have a person who's sort of maintaining justice, establishing the
state of justice and then maintaining it, you get this series and judges of
escalating cycles where Israel or in judges usually some parts.
thereof, some tribe or tribes within Israel. Fall into disobedience. And then come, because of
they fall into disobedience, God removes his protection from them and they get conquered by some
outside force, mediates Philistines, whomever, Moabites. And then God raises up a judge who doesn't
doesn't hear any cases, right? The judge's job is to...
judge, meaning to reestablish justice, he comes in, over throws the oppressors, and then
the cycle repeats.
And as you go through the book of judges, the cycle gets worse and worse and more and more
violent and bloodier and bloodier, and the deliverance gets shorter and shorter and more
and more partial.
there is no one to sort of establish and maintain an appropriate
status quo of holiness and justice and peace. And the book of judges is using that as
the argument for this is why we need to have a king to be that person who does that, to
be the one who establishes divine justice and then maintains it in the face of sin and injustice
within Israel. Because I mean God was doing that in the book of judges, right? But
But...
to disastrous consequence.
Whereas when you have a king and so there is someone, for example, who is enforcing the Torah.
So there is someone who, when you get caught stealing, is now making sure that you pay the restitution.
Right, and repent.
Rather than things getting so horrible that Israel gets conquered, right?
There is a maintenance right of justice.
within the kingdom. And so the king is not sort of doing this independently. It's not that,
oh, well, once they get a human king, he does that. And so then God doesn't have to.
It's that the king is functioning as an icon of God as the great king.
And his core is sort of functioning as an icon of the divine.
Council. Right? God shares his rule over his creation with first the angelic beings and
then later humanity and the same way the king obviously his rule is administered by these
people. Right? And this is an icon then of God and his government of the creation. And
that sense of icon or image works in both directions.
meaning on one hand, the king and the other members of his government have a responsibility
to image God in what they're doing.
So it's God's justice that they're enforcing, not their own whims, not their own preferences,
not their own power, not their own authority, right?
But God's, right.
But and then the people have a responsibility.
in turn to treat them like icons of God and His divine counsel.
Right, to venerate them.
Yeah.
Right.
To honor them in that way.
Even if, and this is why, right, even if the king is a dishonorable cuss, right?
And there are plenty of those in the Old Testament if you've read very much of it, right?
In fact, most of them.
Right.
Yeah.
And that's in case I forget to come back to it later, that's going to stay
true. Most Byzantine Epirus and most Zars are not saints. Right? Not even close. Yeah,
they often kind of opposite. Actually. Yes. Right. So this veneration is not, oh, this is a good
king. David is a really good king. So him will venerate. But Saul, uh, Jeremy, right.
as the icon of God, right? You honor
you give respect to that office because by doing that you are honoring and giving
that honor and respect to God. Yeah it's like my dad used to say when he was in
the Navy, he would say you have to salute what's on the collar even if there's
nothing above it. There you go. That's what my favorite saying is from when my dad
I was the baby.
It's still probably used.
Yeah.
So that's, and again, this is all by the way.
Again, I don't want to go back to all this time.
But this is all venerate means.
Yeah, honor.
It's just giving something to the respect that's due to it.
At the order that's due to it based on what it is.
So another important point though is that,
The king in his court functioning as an icon in this way, or in both these ways, in both directions,
right? Is a, again, a deliberate and drastic departure from what's going on in the other nations,
or in the nations, where the pagan kings are not icons of the gods. They're idols. In the sense that
the king himself is one of the bodies of the God.
He is an embodiment of the God.
Offer him worship, not just respect worship,
like you're offering sacrifices to him.
He's receiving sacrifices.
Right.
And so David, right, is an image of God.
Pharaoh is an idol of Horace
to whom the people offered worship.
Right, you will find lots of people.
proclaiming praises to David in the Old Testament. That's not idolatry.
Yeah. I mean, we should remember, like, if you say, and I would never say this,
but if you say that Striper is the greatest rock band of all time, you have
venerated Striper just by saying that. So just putting that out there, everybody.
What if you call a particular Striper cover band the greatest Striper tribute
band of all time.
I would be willing to do that.
Okay.
Would you not have to listen to all Striper Tribute bands first?
You might.
I mean, how many are...
And are you up for that?
Is any human up for that?
There is actually a friend of mine named Ed Bell.
So Ed, if you're listening, I know he's probably already done it.
So...
It is the lead singer of Striper Ted Cruz.
That's the big question.
and or the zodiac killer. Anyway
Um, yes.
But so we see, we see this attitude of, of veneration very clearly in the story stories,
the whole narrative where David is on the run from Saul where David will have nothing
to do with killing Saul.
the whole idea that he is the Lord's anointed. He is the King. Right? Therefore, he is the image of God's authority.
Anything David did to him, right,
would be effectively doing that to God.
And so he is not willing to do that and in fact
this goes all the way up to when the amulacate who saw, saw, die, caused a David and claims
he killed him to claim a reward. David cuts him down or he's standing. For having claimed
to kill Saul, even though Saul's trying to kill David, right, made several direct, direct
attempts on David's life, right?
Yeah.
You'll solve nothing to do with this.
This is part of where we're getting this.
This isn't just me, hey, he's orthodox,
he's gotta try to shove that icon stuff into everything.
Right, no, this is there in the text.
Right?
This is how David understands Saul's kingship.
And therefore his own kingship.
And how the scriptures understand kingship.
And so this, right, obviously, as we mentioned,
we talked about different anointed people.
especially kings when we were talking about the Messiah in that previous episode.
And so technically right, the anointed king David is the Messiah in that sense.
He's the anointed king.
And so we also understand especially the Davidic kingship.
This was very clearly understood before Jesus of Nazareth was born.
on this earth. It was very clearly understood that David was the icon, the image of the Messiah who was going to come.
We see people in the Gospels, especially the synoptic Gospels, who cry out to Jesus for healing and as an expression of their faith, they call him the Son of David.
Right. That's calling him the Messiah.
The other...
understood, David is sort of this image, this icon of the Messiah who's going to come.
And so then there's going to be this natural transition in understanding afterwards.
We're not jumping there quite yet.
But after the coming of Christ, that King's post, the advent of Christ, are understood
as icons of Christ.
Right?
Looking back.
But we'll get into that more as we move forward.
So a couple more notes sort of on Old Testament kingship.
One important thing, and we talked about this quite a bit in the Melchizedek episode,
is that of course priest and king are divided in the Old Covenant.
Yeah, there's no priest kings.
Right, and that's as opposed to everywhere else.
Where there were priest kings.
And that's up to...
and including the Roman Emperor was the pontifex Maximus, right? He was the great high priest of the Roman Empire, who had responsibilities to himself offer sacrifices.
He didn't just pay for sacrifices, get priests of pagan gods to sacrifices. The Roman Emperor was responsible to do sacrifices. We'll come back to that.
But we talked about, we've talked about that division goes back to Moses and the
issue with circumcising his son and how sort of the the
eldership and the Levitical priesthood was also separated
later at the Golden Calf.
And you can see sort of the the
the real power of this division right when
Saul's sort of final failure is that remember he gets impatient
with
Samuel not showing up at time and decides to go and offer the sacrifices himself. Yeah, which makes him behaving exactly like one of the pagan god kings. Right.
Not exactly like. Well, okay. Sorry, but I'm like, he being a little hyperbolic. Yes, he didn't receive sacrifices himself. But,
but he did act as a priest king, you should always say, right?
illegitimately right of course how that's ultimately reunited right in Christ
in a certain way. We'll talk a little more about that later too. And of course with this role,
as we already saw a little bit in Deuteronomy 17, with this role as the King, as the oldest brother,
as the icon of the King's
of God, the icon of Christ on earth, also meant that the King is held to a higher standard
and to a higher judgment, faces a greater judgment.
This is a basic principle all through the Scriptures, including in the New Testament.
Think about Christ saying, from him who has been given much, much will be required.
Everything St. Paul says about not many of you should presume to be teachers, right?
especially true, of course, of the kings. And what we see when we look at the way the prophets
come, both in what are sometimes called, genre-wise, the historical books, the former prophets,
when the prophets come to confront kings there, and also within the latter prophets,
the prophets proper when they're talking about the kings and leaders and rulers of Israel,
and even other countries, other nations.
The basis of judgment is basically
what is laid out in Psalm 82 or 81 in the Greek,
which is the basis on which, as we've talked about,
that Psalm before, the gods of the nations are judged.
Yeah, the spirits.
Yeah, I mean, like the first verse of Psalm 82, of course,
says the God stands.
up in the divine counsel and renderers judgment, right? And then it says, what the basis of
the judgment is, like this is kind of like reading out the charges against them. And also
like this is what you should have done, right? So here's what it is starting with verse
two, how long will you judge unjustly and show partiality to the wicked? Give justice to
the weak and the fatherless, maintain the right of the afflicted and the destitute, rescue
the week and the needy, deliver them from the hand of
the wicked. And so the idea, of course, is that these fallen gods, these fallen angels,
have not been doing what he told them to do, but instead have been judging unjustly and
giving partiality. You know, they've been favoring the wicked.
Right. Right. And not protecting the people. Yes. And so, right, the role that was assigned
these angelic beings at right at uh
the Babel at the dividing of the nations was to shepherd them in general and in particular
to shepherd them back to God.
Right?
Say, the iness is the area of a guy talks about this too as we mentioned before.
And they fail to do it.
But this pattern, this is the same thing the prophets condemned the Kings for.
So we see that the king...
worship has this kind of angelic ministry to it, meaning it is also the job of any given
king, Israel's king especially, right?
But also the kings of the other nations to shepherd those people and to shepherd them
ultimately back to God.
Yeah, so it's a scientific role.
Right.
And that's what
We see this pattern when it talks about the saints that have a new experience,
the first resurrection and revelation, or when it talks about the saints and the new heavens and the new earth,
this language is used of raining, ruling and raining, of being enthroned with Christ,
being part of the Divine Council, that is paralleled with the Inchellic ministry.
right, but you also have this ruling reign in kingship.
government language, right? And those two things bleed into each other. Right? So the king
ultimately, ultimately, to sum this up, what you ultimately get at with the king's responsibility,
starting with learning and studying the Torah and keeping it fully,
in serving as the image of God on earth to establish justice.
right, and performing this function that was otherwise assigned to the angels.
Ultimately, the command that's given to the king is theosis.
That's the ultimate command that's given to the king.
And this is part of why Christ then is the ultimate king, because he is
in his person.
the perfect bringing together of our human nature and God, and the divine nature,
are united in his person. And so he is the ultimate king by perfectly fulfilling
that. So yes, the king was particularly, particularly called to that. And this is
why
You see in the language regarding saints in the New Covenant, in the New Testament.
Again, St. Paul is saying, do you not know that we will judge angels?
This connection to the, those are church are a royal priesthood.
this connection of kingship already kingship within the kingdom right with Christ as the king
and us as
as vassals, this is also deeply connected
to the theosis language of our salvation.
Yeah, I mean, you know, St. Athanasius in his
On the Incarnation, which a lot of people like to quote
that one line, you know, God became the human
so that man might become God or become
divinized or whatever.
But like the whole snapy, it is a quit.
It is snappy, yeah.
I mean, don't put it on a bumper sticker, whatever.
But although, you know, maybe put it on a bumper sticker,
but someone has.
Yeah, someone has.
So yeah, but like the whole the whole argument that he makes is it's couched within language about adoption
You know that that that's that's where this comes from it's not some
floating doctrine about you know experiencing the Holy Spirit. It's within the context of adoption as sons of God
so
Yes, yes, and if sons then heirs. Yeah indeed
right and so
As I mentioned, this isn't just a question of Israel's king.
This is every king, right?
Every king.
The kings of the nations, the corrupt ones, the evilest ones, right, all had power and
authority given to them by God.
He was the source of any power and authority they had.
And therefore, we're responsible, had this higher level of responsibility.
Yeah, I mean Jesus.
Jesus says that to a pagan ruler, right? He says it to Pontius Pilate, right? When he's standing in front of him, John chapter 19 verse 11
Jesus answered him that is pilot. You would have no authority over me at all unless it had been given you from above
Therefore he who delivered me over to you has the greater sin. In other words, it all power is derivative
but you know ultimately
the where does all that power come from? It comes from
God permits even the bad kings to be the king.
Yes, and then holds them accountable.
Yeah, at the end.
Right.
And so this pattern of kingship from the Old Testament
and the way it's used and continues into the New Testament,
we're going to be moving on mostly in the East as is our want.
But when the western
Roman Empire collapses. When that collapse happens in Western Europe and new social structures have to be built.
It's very natural. It was very natural for the Christians there to return to this tradition and
to bring back anointed kingship as the form of government based on this pattern within
within the Scriptures.
How should we organize ourselves?
Well, you know, spoilers, you're not going to get democracy out of the old testament.
Right?
Or even really the new testament.
Okay.
Nor out of medieval Europeans in general.
No, no, they're not going to come up with this.
And don't come with me with this Athens stuff.
Don't come up with this Athens stuff.
That wasn't real democracy.
Yes.
Any good.
Yeah.
So the one last thing I wanted to say before we go to break about this is
is
Despite what you may have heard, as we just said about democracy, there's a certain
very popular film that once said you don't vote for kings. But actually, in Anglo-Saxon
England, you did, although you probably didn't. Well, it depends on you.
Someone did. Yeah, someone did, but it wasn't the average guy. It wasn't the average
out in the fields. Yeah no it you know it would be the
the the the the the nobles often the lower nobles included you know the the
bishops the abbots the dukes the earls the thanes they get to vote for the king
it's not primogeniture in Anglo-Saxon England and the reason why I point that
out so they they have a big meeting called the witan yamut so the witan is all
the sort of the wise you for you to say yeah it is and but they would have
they would vote right I mean it would sometimes be the son of the previous
but not required.
The reason why I point all that out is because at the ceremony where he becomes king, the
king has to swear a bunch of oaths that are considered to bind him to the people and
require him to do certain things.
And so it's a Christian notion of kingship.
It's different from the kind of kingship of just might, that is the pagan style.
the sense of responsibility to the people.
And of course, the fact that he gets elected, there's that sense of responsibility too.
Again, as they say about feudalism, in democracy theoretically, it's your vote that counts,
but in feudalism it's your count that votes.
So that's kind of true in Anglo-Saxon England.
But yeah, this idea that the king is responsible, he's not just the biggest guy who can do whatever
the heck he wants.
So all right, well that said, let's go to our first break.
and we'll be right back with the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners with help from Faith Tree Resources.
Are you?
anxious to grow in your faith, but struggle to carve out time for spiritual
disciplines like prayer or reading holy scripture? You're not alone. That's
why Faith Tree Resources created the Encounter app. This completely free app for
your iPhone or Android device is designed to make the daily habit of prayer
attainable for everyone, no matter how full your schedule is. The app also
includes daily scripture readings that allow you to listen to the passages
being read aloud. So whether you've got a long commute to work or
your hands full with kids, the encounter app makes it easy to get into a daily rhythm
of prayer and reflection.
Join the thousands of Orthodox Christians around the world who gather daily to pray for
the church as the church.
Download the free encounter app today at faithtree.org.
That's faithtree.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks voice of Steve. I actually might be next week seeing the voice of Steve and
the whole person of Steve really because I was gonna say I don't know that you'll
see his voice per se. I see a voice. That's actually a line from mid-summer
nice stream if I remember correctly. I see a voice. There you go.
That was deliberate irony, though.
I think it's true.
It's true.
Wait, there's irony in Shakespeare.
I have no idea.
Yeah, welcome back.
It's the second half of the show.
Again, you can give us a ring at 855 Afraidiu.
Again, that's 855-237-2346.
So we spent the first part talking about kingship in the Bible.
And now we're going to start talking about kingship
as we start to move.
through history, particularly Rome, because you know that's one of the big questions,
not the only question or the Orthodox Church history, but it's certainly one of the big questions
about how community is organized within Christian history. So the Roman Empire is.
But let's go to before they were an empire at all, right? And they're just
Yes, beatin' on the atrustkins.
Yeah.
So yeah, we're actually, we are going to get to the title of the episode in the second half at least.
Yeah, that's crazy.
So yeah, we hear your feedback and okay, gotta be honest, we don't do anything about it, but we do hear it.
I read it.
So we are going to Rome or Rome word, right?
And so before we can talk about...
as we just alluded to, St. Constantine.
And I know there are people who flinch
every time I say that.
That's part of why I say it so often.
We have to talk a little bit about the whole
I concept of the Roman Emperor, right?
And the Roman Empire is such, right?
So Rome, not built in a day, as it turns out,
took a long time.
Yeah. And so Rome in particular was not a big fan of the idea of kings. The early kings
of Rome and their own understanding of their history were referred to as the tyrants. That's
where we get the word. The tyrannis. And so those were the battle days of the
six separate haven't changed.
I say.
Um, we're dog controversial.
There we go.
Um, it's the motto of the state in which I was born six.
Simperty.
Siding with the the assassins.
Siding with the assassins.
Okay.
I'm just putting that out there.
Um, we're talking about say, Constantine the great.
You don't, you don't need a more street cred with that faction.
Okay.
It's not a type of.
Um, so.
So, roam then forms.
a republic centered around the Senate. And the Senate was sort of deliberately constructed
in order to have a distribution of power so that power would never sort of overly
conglomerate in any one person. So you have different roles like the consul, like you have
these different roles, but there's always two, three, a lot of times these are chosen by
a lot. There are different methods, different periods of Roman history.
by which even when you have to have somebody who's kind of in charge,
you make it a couple people and you pit them against each other in various ways
right to sort of make sure nothing gets out of hand. And this of course, if
you're familiar with American history or you've ever been to Washington DC and
looked around, you know that the Roman Republic and the functioning of the
Roman Senate was sort of the deliberate basis of the American system of
government right they were the same way trying to make it
it on will be and make it difficult for any particular person to do anything.
Yeah, I mean, no, when they're not getting things done, that's by design.
Yes, that's a feature, not a bug, according to the framers, right?
So but the Senate had this too, right?
And so this is why, right, when you get to Julius Caesar, you get to Caesar.
at first, you know, the same kind of
ploy he's sort of pitted.
against Pompey as the other great general Pompeys out annexing things in the East, Caesars
out dividing Gaul and three parts. And we tried to play them against each other, but ultimately
Caesars the canier player and commits the great crime of ambition.
Stunt and beating he wants to be the guy
the Senate doesn't like that and I really wish we were doing this episode next week on the
Iads of March. It would be perfect, but he gets stabbed 23 times on the floor of the Senate
at two birthday. Yeah. And, right, that's always to tyrants, right?
not not exactly always because it's only one more generation and
get one. So this kind of then repeats itself in the wake of Caesar's death. You have Mark
Antony who was his heir. You have Octavian who is his nephew. Pitted against each other.
Octavian wins the battle of Actium. He becomes Caesar Augustus. He succeeds where Julius
failed and now he have a Roman Empire. The Senate sticks around. There is still a
Robyn Senate but...
For most of the history of the Roman Empire, they're not doing a whole lot.
Yeah, they're mostly, it eventually devolves into rich people with titles.
Yeah, they're just kind of a nobility of sorts.
Yeah.
So the title emperor, right?
But even with this being the case even with a gossess
have a basically total power and the people following after him in the Giulio
Claudian dynasty and then afterwards.
Weilding pretty close to ultimate power. Later on, much later in the history of the
empire, as we're going to talk about here in a minute, they fall back into old
patterns of sort of defying up authority again, having an emperor in the West
and one in the East and a Augustus and right, trying to
and pitting them against each other on purpose, right?
But even when Augustus is fully feeling his oats, even when he's having
ascolas rewrite the history of the empire to focus on him.
Coming to fruition of all of Roman history, he's not able to take the title king for himself.
Because Rex is not happening.
Right? That's the bad title.
We don't I mean he's more king than they ever were but but still
don't call yourself that. Yeah, so the title becomes Imperator, which is where we get Emperor
and Empire ultimately too. Yes, yeah, yeah, which goes from Imperium, right. But the
Imperator before Caesar is a military title that was awarded as an honorary title after a general
We're all headwinded.
great victory in war. So Iparato literally means like commander, the one who commands
or the one who orders, the one who puts an order like musters and army. Right. But because
of the context in which it was granted that was granted after achieving these great victories,
it came to have sort of the connotation of conqueror, right, like the victorious general, right.
And so...
If impirator is sort of the conqueror, the orderer, then the Imperium is the conquered or
ordered area, the region that's under his command, under his orders, under his law giving.
And so, see, a empire grows, there's a number of administrative issues. Really, there was always an
Eastern and Western Roman Empire. Right? As we just mentioned...
Caesar was in the West and Pompey was in the East, right?
There were always, there were cultural differences with,
with the way Greek was used,
although Greek was used even at the Western Roman Empire
for a good while.
And other cultural differences,
but it becomes sort of formal, administratively formal
later on.
As we mentioned, you get an emperor,
you get in the gusset in each half.
You have sort of these four figures who have different powers, again, trying to break things up.
But now the aforementioned St. Constantine arrives, and not a Saint yet.
And inherits the title of Augustus in the West while he's in Britain from his father,
when his father dies.
And decides that he is going to roll things back and he's going to become the Emperor Emperor.
He's going to become the single Emperor, the monarch of the Roman Empire.
And so now we're going to talk about St. Constantine.
And we're going to be doing now a lot of myth busting.
Yeah
Because there is this ironic thing where
Seikot State is literally the best documented emperor in Roman history.
Yeah, I mean we know we have more evidence about his life and all the things that he did than any of the rest of him.
So anything we have want to say about St. Constantine, you got to look at that evidence.
Yes, we have the text of every loggy issue to Zemper.
We have...
the text of nearly as far as we could tell nearly every letter official letter he wrote as emperor.
We have all of these multiple biographies from contemporaries who lived at the same time.
We have all of this documentation about St. Constantine. And yet somehow,
Somehow, every bizarre wild conspiracy theory on Earth that you could think...
think of has been attached to say,
Constantine somehow by somebody somewhere, right?
But the vast majority of them are just made up.
Yeah, just made up.
And so as we go through, as we talk about some of these,
if we have an idea of where this might have come from,
like sometimes it's like, okay, well,
This idea seems to be based on a misunderstanding of x.
Right? We'll talk about that. But there's a lot of these where there's no X, right? There's like no way
on Earth to come up with this. It's just nonsense.
But you can experience your theories.
But some of this stuff, you know, we're calling it nonsense. We're calling it just like intelligent people
regurgitate this stuff, some of this stuff that has just no basis in history.
Right?
It's amazing to me, right?
That, especially when there, you know,
go a couple of emperors down the road, right?
Like, could stand to you or something.
Right? Like, somebody less documented,
pit it on him, right?
Like, but anyway.
So, of course the...
The first thing we need to talk about with St. Constantine is the vision he has.
Yes, this is why it kind of when he sort of really steps on to the stage of history for most people.
Right, and this is related to his conversion to Christianity, which is what we're going to talk about next.
And so this is before the Battle of the Milvian Bridge, which ends up being the decisive battle in terms of him
Defeat
his co-emperor, shall we say, just for the sake of ease of argument. Right? That's the other
claimants to the imperial throne. And so he has, now there are different accounts of this.
So, Eusebius of Cessaria, who's the Eusebius who wrote the ecclesiastical history, was like
The biggest
This is a simple, st. Constantine in the history of earth.
Really it's depressing, right?
It's like pulling yourself together, man.
When you read some of this stuff he writes about, about st. Constantine.
And I'm someone who calls him st. Constantine and I feel this way reading UCB's.
Yeah.
And so a lot of stuff sounds very embellished, shall we say.
So.
So we also have an account of this dream from lactantius.
lactantius is more reserved about this kind of stuff.
So in terms of my own approach to this stuff, if both UCBS and lactantius talk about it,
I think it's on secure footing, right, to go with.
So, and you see me as records of stuff that's just weird.
Like he has before
St. Constantine became a Christian
UCBS has him in Britain having this vision of Apollo and Apollo predicting he's gonna raid for 30 years and you're like a
Apollo
Right, it seems a little odd. I mean because you said you see is I mean, he's a little bit of a wacky Christian, but he is a Christian
Yeah, yeah, yeah
Yeah, yeah, yeah, and notice folks notice folks who rely on UCBS a lot
not Saint Eucelius. No, he's a historian, he's an important historian from the period.
Well, he wrote theological stuff too that's important in various ways, but he was at least a semi-Aryan,
right? He was not that orthodox Christian. So, but, you know, being a bit heretical does not mean
you're wrong about history, right? You can't say true things about events that happened in your
your own time.
Right.
So he's an important person.
Yeah, yeah.
So I look for UCBS Lack of Tentious crossover
when it comes to, to say, Constantine.
And both of them record him.
So with UCBS there's multiple visions
and different things happening.
But both of them have him before the Battle of Billy of Bridge,
he has this dream in which Christ appears to him
and tells him to put a particular sign
sign on the shields of his men.
to protect them in battle.
And so, you see, B.S.
It's kind of vague as to exactly what this is.
It's just sort of the sign of the cross.
Yeah.
But like Tantius describes it in some more detail
as the key row symbol,
the key in rowing the Greek letters,
Greek letters, right? The key looking kind of like an
in English and the capital row looking is the thing that looks kind of like a
shepherd's crook like it's hooked over at the top and they're super imposed
over each other. You've probably seen this symbol. Yeah you've probably seen this
symbol in the Orthodox Church and or the Roman Catholic Church still uses it.
not with the keys and everything.
Sorry, but
but just the civil of the key in the row, which of course are the first two letters in Christos and which also forms a cross shape.
And so this,
St. Constantine did this,
St. Constantine won the battle,
St. Constantine became emperor after the battle.
because of this, he issued the edict of Milan, the edict of toleration.
that legalized Christianity, but all other religions too, right, to be fair. Granted,
broad legal toleration, but it wasn't just like, okay, we're not going to persecute you anymore,
because within the Roman Empire, persecution was always sort of localized at different times
in different periods, right? It wasn't just perpetually we're killing all the Christians we find
for 300 years.
Yeah, it was kind of...
sporadic and local sporadic right so it wasn't just hey we're not gonna do that anymore
It was also right property that had been seized
from Christianity
For being an illicit religion was returned
Right there was restitution made from the Roman imperial government to Christian clergy Christian institutions
Right Christian people yeah, and and you know this is not the this is not the point of course at which
Christianity becomes like the established official religion of the Roman Empire. That doesn't happen for no 50 something years under
Thedosius close to 70. Yeah. Yeah
Two generations passed before that happens. Yeah exactly. So actually so before we move on to the next point we have someone who's calling in
So we've got Robbie on the line. So Robbie are you there?
I am here. Can you hear me? We hear you Rob.
me welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. I'm glad you called because someone recently
asked whether it was no longer a live show with actual callers. And I said, well, I guess
it's done then. So you've saved the show. Welcome back. Yes. Yeah. I think there's just
so many episodes to work through now that no one's trying to get caught up. Yeah. So
Alright Robbie, so welcome and what is your question for us this evening?
Yeah, thank you. So first of all, I'm a big fan of the show. Thank you for everything that you guys do.
But yeah, my question is about kind of this idea of coronation as a sacrament.
I know you guys are going to talk a lot more about this. So maybe I'm jumping the gun.
But I specifically wanted to ask, there seems to be this conflict, I don't know if it's
a conflict or a development to change.
or something where early on it looks like the patriarch is crowning the emperor and or later
like the king and like the king of Yugoslavia or something. But then later it seems as though
like the czar and I don't know maybe some emperors you would know better. Kind of purposefully
crown themselves seemingly as a
symbol of their authority comes directly from God
and not through the church.
At least that's what I've read from people
who talk about this.
So I don't know.
That's kind of one of the parts that kind of doesn't sit
well with me.
It seems like if it's a sacrament, it
should be like a sacrament that comes from the church
and everything and why the flip flop.
So I don't know if you guys know anything about that,
but that's always been a great curiosity to me ever since I
start looking into this
Yeah, well, so actually at the end of this half, we're going to take people on a little walk through a particular
coronation ceremony for an emperor. So hang on to that. That'll be fun. And it's one of the later Byzantine
emperors. But I am a, I can't name any names off the top of my hands. So maybe you know, Father Stephen. But I
have, I have, remember reading about some European kings that do crown themselves. You know, there's a sense of,
You know that there's this.
that as you said, well that's mine, I'm the person with the power here anyway, so give me.
But I would say though that in general the standard is that the king is crowned by whoever the chief
bishop in his realm is. That's what typically occurs. Certainly I'm sure that's what we're going to see,
not too long with King Charles III is that the archbishop of Canterbury is going to put the crown on
and I said, you know that it's not something he does for himself.
I don't know, Father Steven, do you know?
of any Christian kings that are crowning themselves?
Yeah, well so there's of course, I mean famously there's the Charlemagne
argument about whether he crowned himself or not. Yeah, I knew that was a little fuzzy.
But also, so in terms of Robbie's direct question, a lot of people now, I mean this was everybody
learned about this 20 years ago when I was coming into the church but a pair.
Nobody does now.
Or at least I have reason to believe that a lot of people haven't.
About what happened from the 16th century on with the Russian church,
that right, Peter the Great gets rid of the patriarch.
Yeah, there's no patriarch, there's just the Holy Sinod.
Right, and he does that deliberately to pattern the government of the Russian Orthodox church
after the government of the Lutheran Church is in Germany.
And then in later periods, they...
bring in Jesuits to teach it all the seminaries.
Right, so there's this period of time
where the Russian church gets subjected
to the Russian state.
Those Zars are not superpious people
in the sense of orthodox piety at least, right?
And so a lot of the traditional practices
the orthodox church get subjugated to
the whim of the emperor or empress
if we're talking about Catherine, right?
And so lots of things happen like that
because the church did not have the power,
right, well, obviously you can't have this art
getting crowned by the patriarch if there isn't one.
And so lots of things like that happen,
lots of things even by people who are saints,
They're saints because...
of how they live their lives, right? But you have texts coming out of Russian seminaries
and Russian church officials at that time where you find Lutheranism or Roman Catholic Jesuit theology
or at least terminology all over the place, right? And it's not that they were heretics,
it's not that they weren't really Orthodox. They were, it's just the time they grew up in,
the education.
And they received, that's the terminology they learned.
And so in their lives, they're clearly practicing the Orthodox faith in a true way, right?
Or at least the truest way they could, given the material realities of the time and place
that they lived.
And that's why there are saints.
But a lot of the outer forms in that get subjugated to the whims of some very not-holy
people in the Russian civil government, which really, the further you go into the modern
age is deliberately trying to compete with and pattern itself after the modern governments
of Western Europe.
That's sort of a inferiority complex.
And so yeah, a lot of things like that unfortunately happen.
I mean, we're at part eight of our sacrament series.
But if you go to a lot of the theological manuals,
that are published during that period when the Jesuits are teaching in all the Russian
seminaries, they'll say there's seven sacraments, and they give the Roman Catholic list.
Yeah.
Right?
Whereas if you look at older stuff or orthodox stuff that's coming from places not affected
by the Russian crown and what it's doing, you'll see longer lists.
You'll see lists of ten, lists of twelve.
So yeah, I would chalk up those incidents with this
are to that same kind of foreign spirit from Europe, making
intrusions into the civil government of Russia.
And that isn't to me any kind of argument
against the Orthodox faith, because I mean,
there are iconoclast emperors within the Byzantine Empire.
at least where the uppers was a
monothelite. There's that person.
with all kinds of different sympathies all through, you know, and the iconoclast emperors
were killing people and torturing people for having icons, you know. So there's no guarantee
that any given emperor will be a saint that he will respect the church and subject himself
to the church any more than there was any guarantee that the king of Israel would actually
read the Torah and try to practice the commandments.
So yeah.
Yeah, you're right that those things happened.
And I think that spirit, that modern spirit
for Western Europe that infected the government of Russia
for centuries is responsible for it.
There you go.
That's my take at least.
Does that help, Robbie?
Yeah, that's very helpful.
Thank you, fathers.
I love the show.
And yeah, my wife and I are actually in the process
of uh
my son of joining the Orthodox Church right now. So a lot of that is because of you guys. So thank you.
Thanks be to God. Thanks be to God. All right. Well, thank you for calling.
Okay. So the question now that I know is on everybody's mind is, did Constantine really convert
to Christianity? Yes. There you go. Good night. Okay. Um, it's been a while since I did one of those.
Yeah, so
Yeah, this is one of those things.
So part of the problem is the ludicrous level of
presentism that's pre-supposed when this topic is even
addressed by contemporary people, including scholars.
So the question
As it is commonly asked in the present day, did Constantine convert to Christianity?
Is understanding conversion to Christianity as a combination of some kind of emotional experience or feeling with him changing his ideas or beliefs about certain things?
So
A bunch of problems there. First of all, as people who listen to the show know, that's not
what conversion is.
Yeah. You're not...
Crystans are not going to come in the end to judge how everyone feels in their heart.
Yeah. Or what everyone thinks in their head. So, that's a problem. It's a bigger problem
for anybody who's trying to work as a historian because how on earth can you determine the feelings
and someone's heart.
and the ideas in their head.
Right.
Like good luck with that, right?
Yeah, I mean, there's no point in the canonical tradition
regarding conversion or the baptismal service
where anyone says, you know, how do you feel?
Or like, are you sincere?
I mean, there is a line, of course,
I believe in him as king and God,
but that's really like, I'm faithful to him as king and God.
Like, this is what I'm going to do.
You know?
Right.
Yeah.
And so the main, all of the main arguments that are made by people, not all, most will
get to the other one in a little bit.
The main arguments that are made for why, when someone is going to say he didn't really
become Christian are all examples of where he tolerated Roman paganism.
Yeah, right. So he lets he doesn't burn down all the pagan temples
He doesn't require all the senators to convert to Christianity.
He doesn't immediately say, no more coins with pagan symbols on them.
We're going to print Jesus on all the coins now or something.
Right, so he doesn't do those things, right?
And therefore
he didn't really become a Christian. The presupposition there, of course, is that Christianity is completely intolerant.
The presupposition there is that if he was really a Christian, he would have immediately gone on a witch hunt.
Outlawed a lot of them. Yeah, kill him all.
which falls to category of what? Right? Because there aren't a bunch of
Christians around in the third century. Even at the
the bitterest depths of persecution,
who are writing things, talking about how,
oh, we need to get revenge.
One of these days, we're gonna get power
and we're gonna go and kill all these pagans
the way they killed us and torture them,
the way they tortured us.
There aren't any Christians writing those things,
because that's not how Christianity works.
Hmm, right?
We have a rich theology of martyrdom
that was taken over from the Jewish concept
of martyrdom in the second temple pier.
Okay, we're not looking for, we're not, we're never looking for revenge.
So why would you expect Constantine to do that if he became a Christian?
Right?
That's just a prejudice that a given person has against Christianity and a caricature
of Christians that they have.
And since Constantine doesn't turn into that after his conversion, oh, he must not have
really converted.
We kill them all.
Get our all to you.
Don't love Jesus.
Yes, a colossally stupid argument, right?
Yeah.
A colossally stupid argument or set of arguments, right?
But so if we look at the only thing we have access to, what St. Constantine did after
his conversion.
And as we already mentioned, we have unparalleled access to all the things he did, right?
the paints are very different picture of change.
Right off the bat. Right off the bat.
St. Constantine establishes himself as the sole emperor of Rome.
He is now emperor at all.
He makes, he assembles a Roman triumph, right, which was a large military procession,
like a huge military parade.
Yeah, to make to the city of Rome.
Victory parade that you do after you win.
Right.
And so he organizes this.
marches into Rome and all the ones in the past, right?
The emperor marches into Rome, proceeds to the temple
of Jupiter on Palatine Hill,
and there as the pontifax Maximus offers sacrifices
to Jupiter in thanks for his victory and his enthronement.
Say Constantine marches into the city,
it goes directly to his palace, right?
does not pass.
Jupiter Temple does not collect 200 dead goats or whatever. My analogy is breaking down.
He goes directly to his residence. Did not offer the pagan sacrifices. Now our folks who want to say,
I mean that in itself is a huge piece of evidence that the conversion was real. Right? The fact that he
It breaks with centuries of tradition.
By not giving thanks to Jupiter for his victory.
and instead giving credit to Christ.
That alone, right, is monumental.
As a break.
Right.
So our, no, he didn't really convert people, right?
Their response is, well, technically his victory
was in a civil war.
Not over four in the enemies.
Yeah, I mean, if you're gonna make that claim,
then you have to show that no Roman emperor
Did that
that kind of thing when being victorious in the Civil War.
And you know what?
They did.
Yeah, Augustus sure celebrated.
Right.
And this wasn't just a one off for St. Constantine.
It isn't just, oh, that one time,
he didn't offer pagan sacrifices, right?
He himself never offered any more pagan sacrifices.
despite having been apprised.
And...
And he never tried to offer the Eucharist himself, meaning he abandoned the priesthood, which
he had by right of being the emperor.
Right.
Yeah.
And that included, he ended pagan sacrifices before his armies went into battle and instituted
having Christian priests come and offer the Eucharist.
Yeah, that's a big.
He issued a law that Christian clergy within the empire were exempt from public service.
There were a couple different types of public service in the Roman Empire.
There was of course military service.
But there was also just sort of public work service where you get kind of drafted to do
work in the community, right, labor that you're eligible for.
clergy were exempted from that so that they
could serve the liturgy and commemorate Saint Constantine at the liturgy in prayer because
this is where the word liturgy comes from. It means public works. So the Christian liturgy,
Christian prayers, Christian worship was reclassified by Saint Constantine as public service offered
to the Empire, so they were immune from all other public service.
when he built Constantinople.
Okay?
It's a constant built Constantinople and made the pagans pay for it.
Literally.
Right.
The Christians were exempt from the tax.
He made pagans pay the tax.
And this cause, this was a sort of passive aggressive way
to close down pagan temples.
because he took as tax money the money that would have gone to those pagan temple endowments.
And so a lot of the pagan temples ended up closing because they couldn't afford to keep functioning.
Because their money was going to build Constantinople, which was the first city built in the history
of the world with no pagan temples in it.
And yes, that includes cities in ancient Israel as we unfortunately know from the Old Testament.
Yeah, right.
Right.
That's...
No peg of temples within the city of of
Constantinople
ever
In 325 he shut down
gladiatorial combat
Which you know that thing that he did in life will echo into eternity
Yes, and you and you are not entertained
That's right
They're making a secret.
to that movie did you know that? I did not know that. Russell Crowe is not in it for obvious
reasons, spoilers. So, um, Lamez Rahab was not the sequel to anyway. No, no, that isn't work,
man. Back to the drug board with that film theory. Um, so, uh, say, Constitine also outlawed crucifixion
as a form of capital punishment.
Yeah, he did not outlaw capital punishment. Right.
That's hanging.
That'll be honest here, right?
And I'm sure some people were getting their heads cut off by swords too, probably.
Yeah, but it was mostly hanging instead of crucifixion.
But he got rid of crucifixion because he said it was disrespectful to Christ for them
to crucify people.
One of the most interesting laws he issued was the issue to law that slaves and convicted
criminals could
not be branded except on their feet.
So one of the punishments of the Roman Empire for being convicted of certain crimes, right?
Or when you were a slave to mark you out as a slave, was you would be branded and they
would generally brand you in a very conspicuous place because the idea was you don't want this
slave to be able to cover it up in escape. You don't want, you know, criminals to be able
able to disguise the fact that they were convicted of this crime, you want them to be permanently
marked. So they generally we branded in the face. Yeah.
Because that was really hard to cover up. And in that law, St. Constantine explicitly
says that the reason criminals and slaves can no longer be branded on the face is that
branding, the branding of the face, the just figurement of the face, disrespected the image
of Christ in which the person was created. It's amazing. It's not just like this is
or whatever, but it's actually a theological reason.
Yes.
Yeah.
That that person is in the, even the slave, even the convicted criminal is created in the
image of Christ, and therefore you cannot just figure him in this way.
So of course, right?
There's a collective case there for how he's ruling and how he's thinking after his conversion.
But I think is entirely...
pelling. I'm not saying he had all of his theology worked out correctly. I'm not saying
right, but in terms of, this pagan who's now become the most powerful man on earth,
right, claims to have become a Christian. Let's look at how he governed.
There's this is I think a conclusive evidence that he was at least trying to be a Christian.
Yeah, right. I knew it was at least trying to figure out
out what that meant. No one was making him do this stuff. And it was probably in his, in terms of
just, you know, shoring up his power and stuff, it was not in his best interests, you know, to
change these kinds of policies that it always always kind of sort of worked for Roman Empire,
Emperors, you know, to aggregate. There was not a thousand. They're not like a bunch of powerful
wealthy Christians who are gonna repay him for doing this.
No! Right.
before the edict, before the edict under
dilution, right?
The world of governance seized all the Christian property,
right?
This, Christians had nothing.
They're being tortured, they're being mutilated, right?
Yeah.
So yeah, that whole dog don't hunt.
So probably though the most famous Christian thing
that St. Constituent did was convening the council of Nicaea.
Yes.
Ed, here come the conspiracy theories again.
Yeah, there's so many of these.
I feel like we should just do like, you know, lightning round, naming them off.
Yeah.
All the things that the cowboys have.
Well, some of them require a little more explanation.
That's true.
Yeah.
Yes.
Alright, this is like what?
I don't even know how many I have listed here.
It's like a top 10, top 8, something like that.
Yeah.
Because we could go on forever, list.
if we try to list every weird council,
and I see a conspiracy there.
Okay, so I'm gonna just throw them out and if you have something you have to say about a particular one
Okay, okay, all right. Okay, so the councilman I see it did not I feel like there should be a little bell or something ding
Did not decide what's in the Bible
That I have something to say about it. Okay, yeah
So so this is common right all kinds of very intelligent people say this
Right, uh, and it's just entirely an urban legend that there was some kind of canon
either of the older New Testament or something that was decided at NICIA, that they decided some books were in and somewhere.
It did not happen. It was not even discussed at the Council of NICIA. Now, this is one of the words we're at where
Like I have a theory maybe about how the misunderstanding that started the urban legend, right.
But the more I investigated it, the more I found that that's not at all what happened. So
You will find
testimony that after the Council of Nicaea, St.
Constantine requested 50 copies be made of the Christian scriptures.
So my thought is someone reading that sort of tried to connect the dots and said,
well, wait a minute, like those copies must have had a table of contents.
and therefore de facto
Right, that's a canon list. So, right, like maybe that's where it came from. But as I investigate more,
I discovered upon further research that he actually commissioned 50 gospel books.
So yeah, there's just liturgical gospels that...
The four with the four gospels, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yes, yes. So you can't get a canon list from the four gospels, right?
And the four gospels had been established as the four gospels, at least since the middle of the
the 2nd century, St. E. N. A. S. Toxie.
Yes, so this is at least 200 years.
Yeah.
Yes, he didn't decide which gospels were gospels, right?
Okay, back to the list.
The castle I see it did not.
Also did not, Dean Creed the Roman Catholic Church.
Sorry.
Okay, did not, Dean cover up Jesus's secret family.
So he's Mary Magdalene.
Yes.
Conspiracies, yeah.
Did not change the identity of Jewish people.
What's that about?
I don't know what that's about.
Well, there's variations of this.
There's, there's,
there's, English people were the real Jewish people.
There's, oh, okay.
There's black people were the real Jewish people.
There's a whole series of those where
St. Constantine declared the people who we now know
as Jews to be Jews.
And some other group that actually were the
original Israelites do not be any.
war. Wow. Okay. Alright. Alright. Alright. So British,
Israelism, etc. Alright. The castle of Nicae did not, did not
ding burn any books, any churches or people. Yes. Yes. There was
a functioning Aryan church in Constantinople for another
century after the council of Nicae. How about that? For a hundred
years.
was glorious closed it until when he was the Archbishop of Constantinople.
Yes. So great. There was what right there in the Imperial city? Areas, right? Areas were
not going to kill. They were not getting burnt. Say, Constitutes spent the rest of his life trying,
well, the rest of Areas' life actually, trying to get Areas to be reconciled to the church,
Church. Writing letters to areas, writing letters to bishops.
trying to heal this thing. So not only did he not go and sort kill in all the
aliens, right? Like he was trying to see if we couldn't figure this thing out.
Right? Yeah. So he didn't have to burn any books because they didn't decide on the canon.
Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Okay. So relatedly, the council of nicely did not force
Constantine's theology on anyone because he might have been kind of a semi-Irient.
Yeah, all indicators are that the decision of the council and I see a regarding the deity of Christ
Is not actually was not
Constituent's personal opinion at the time of the council
There you go
All right the council and I see it did not and this should be really obvious everybody
But anyway did not proclaim Jesus to be divine rather than merely human
Well, it's not obvious to Dan Brown
I know, I know that...
That's the thing is people say this to like,
oh, the councilman, they see,
invented the idea that Jesus is God.
I'm like excuse me.
Excuse me.
The areas thought Jesus was God.
Yeah, it was something.
They thought, yes, exactly.
They just thought he was a God rather than the God.
Right.
The big debate in the first couple of centuries,
especially was not so much how or is he God,
but rather is he human?
You know, like, well, and in what sense is he divine?
Yeah, right, right.
In what sense is he divine?
Yeah.
Okay.
The calc of Nysia did not, ding, move Christian worship to Sundays.
I mean, read sorry, LNG white.
Yeah, sorry, LNG white.
I think that's two episodes in a row when we've got, no, it's very Baker Eddie last.
Oh, that's right.
Okay, and the fact that you can't tell white woman her S.E.R.X apart is some
of racism and I have to call you on it publicly.
Maybe I should read my own book.
Yeah.
That would have been...
You know, I wrote it down in my diary, so I wouldn't have to remember.
So, yeah, so that didn't happen.
The Lord's Day.
It's in the pages of the New Testament that Christians were gathering on the Lord's
Day.
Yeah.
The first day of the week, Sunday.
Now, now, that's it.
though I have is when I have a theory again. So there's actually a possible basis for this.
A possible basis of completeness understanding. Yes.
And that's the state constantly did issue a law making Sunday the first day of the week,
the Lord's Day. We'll just say the Lord's Day. Right. Curia key. Right.
a, um, an official day of rest. Meaning. Okay.
Yeah.
What that functionally meant, right?
If you were a farmer, you didn't get any days of rest,
right?
But which was most people.
But in cities, government offices, for example,
the bureaucratic offices of state, right?
The government offices, government functions,
were shut down on the Lord's Day.
Right?
Because everyone, including the government officials,
including the emperor, were in the liturgy.
Right.
Accept.
This is another word of the-
interesting little tidbits when you read the law. There was one government office that stayed open on
the Lord's Day, and that was the Office of Manumission. If you wanted to free a slave, you could go
free a slave on the Lord's Day. That's the one civil government function you were allowed to do.
And once again, testimony to, you know...
Is the only testimony we have to the thoughts and feelings of St. Constantine, right?
But that he understands something going on there
with the Lord's Day and the resurrection. And what's that about?
Nice. Okay, the Councilman I see it did not begin the practice of baptizing babies.
Yes, yes, right? Did not. Sorry, certain groups of baptists.
That's it.
not all Baptist. There are a lot of Baptists who are good, reasonable people who have some
understanding of church history. I mean, most of the folks out there though, most of the
Baptists that I was raised with have never even, I mean, and it's not their fault, but
they've never even heard of the Council of NICIA. Yeah. Not their fault. Don't want to
ever told them about this. Yeah. And finally, the Council of NICIA did not have the option
to change the mode of production in the Empire, which seems like a kind of upstairs thing
to press the D-
to deny. But people have said this, they had a chance to get together and vote to end slavery.
They could have done that. Yes. People have said this recently, very well educated, very smart
people in public who know a lot about history. Who, if I name names on this show, yes, who, if I
name names on this show, I would name, but I don't do that. Yes. Especially what I'm about to say,
something is one of the stupidest things I've ever heard in my life.
Um, but...
So, yes, yes.
A very wise smart intelligent person.
And then a bunch of other at least reasonably intelligent people like retweeted this and
praised this as like the most brilliant thing ever said about how I'm looking at the
council.
The council is now.
Yeah, I don't care.
I'm calling this, I'm saying this person said one of the most colossally stupid things
I've ever heard.
And you can tell of that and I'll explain it to a mid person.
that this will be...
was a horrible missed opportunity because they could have ended slavery.
They could have ended poverty in the Roman Empire.
They could have just voted to do that.
Let's just completely change the economic system under which the entire Roman Empire functions
by 300 bishops voting on it.
Right?
Bishops voting.
Right.
Yes.
about something that the council was not convened to decide.
Right?
and remotely and had no jurisdiction over.
Right, but there's multiple levels to how dumb this is.
So the first level of how dumb it is is,
like we just said,
that would have worked if they tried it.
Right?
That was actually a possibility.
I mean, by the way, we should not say
that we're like pro slavery or anything.
It's just like, no, this was not a possibility.
That was not something they could do. Now there were people at this time, for example, like St. Gregory of this well a little after this time, it's a Gregory of Lisa.
Two subsequent Pascas in his sermon told his people they had to free all their slaves because it was morally wrong for them to claim to own another person created in the image of Christ.
We just talked about how the menu mission office was the one office open on the Lord's day. Right. So yet clearly, Christianity was going to end slavery.
slavery. But you.
can't do that in like a day by a bunch of bishops voting, right? Because an empire is a complex economy
sources of labor and value generation. And you can't just like flip a switch like okay now we're
going to be capitalists, right? I mean, and let's face it, when was the last time that an
you know like an agreed statement vote.
are none by bishops, became immediately effective
to everyone who possibly read it.
Oh, yes.
Yes.
That's not, I wish.
Like I wish, but no.
So, but there's a deeper level of dumb.
There's a deeper level of dumb.
And that deeper level of dumb is not understanding
that there are material preconditions for ideas
to emerge. So part of the reason they could decide to become a capitalist democracy in
325 at the Council of Dicea is that they had no idea what capitalism or democracy were.
These ideas did not exist yet. You can't have capitalism really until you have the
guys.
of enclosure and until you have the idea of commodity production.
At the beginning of industrialization, which didn't exist yet, right? Like the ideas on which
those later ideas were built did not exist yet. Right? So yes, people like St. Gregory of
D.C. could look at the institutional slavery and say this is wrong and say to individual people,
you did not participate in this. Right? But if St. Constantine, let's say they take a...
of OTA and slavery and say, Constitio said, you're right. I hear by issue this law, slavery
is over every what is free. What happens the day after? Who's farming food? Yeah, I mean,
right? Like this requires massive restructuring. So not only could they not have done it, right?
but they could not have even conceived of doing it in 325 AD.
So the idea that somehow was a missed opportunity,
that they are somehow blameworthy.
The fathers of the council and I see are somehow blameworthy,
because they're being too narrow-minded
and just focusing on this theological stuff.
And not, you know, our important, you know,
bourgeois liberal values is ridiculous and absurd.
And one of the stupidest things it's ever been said publicly.
Anyway.
Yeah, they couldn't have done that.
Okay.
This argument is like saying that Vatican one in the middle
of the 19th century should have voted
to abolish the euro, which didn't exist yet.
Right.
Anyway, rant, rant over.
I think this is the first time I've got
out a full on rant like that on the show.
But people who live with me hear them all the time.
Yes.
I'm just, I've heard you rant on whole council
I've got a couple.
times. Okay, fair. Yeah, yeah. Okay, so there's some things with the council of
NYC did do. Yes, now the positive. Let's focus on the positive. Yeah, yeah. We don't need to get into
super detail here, but I think it's just important to kind of debunk a bunch of that. Okay, so yes,
the council of NYC did, you know, make a ruling against Aryanism, though not strictly because
because there were still some semi-urions kind of around.
Then council...
I see a did establish how you're supposed to date POSCA.
The Council of NICA did codify the findings of a bunch of preceding local councils.
Let's see if you actually read the cannons, I'll say, and then this council and this council.
And the Council of NICA did establish the very important precedent of actually holding
ecumenical councils.
So that's why we call it the first ecumenical council.
And they of course tied that back to X15.
in the council of Jerusalem, but.
Oh yeah.
This is a different conception, right?
The idea didn't come out of nothing
because as we just said, ideas don't come out of nothing.
But yeah, they see the same language.
It seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us.
And that's that, that becomes,
that formula gets picked up then
by the other ecumenical councils.
Right, right.
And so they're building on something,
but this then establishes the pattern
it's gonna be used going.
forward. Yeah. Right. And you know, a part of that pattern that a lot of people aren't happy
with and that probably is responsible for a lot of those urban legends at all that we've been
talking about is the fact that the emperor, in this case, St. Constituede, presided at the council.
Yeah, called it and then right beside it right and so again this is
prejudice that's warmed its way deep into our brain of the idea of separation of church and state.
Right? Yeah. If you're an American, if you're not an American,
you may not have separation of church and state per se, but the modern world, the modern West,
at least, definitely has an idea of a sacred sphere and a secular sphere. So there's the church,
and that there's the secular, right?
So there's the church authority.
in the secular authority. Right. And so if you have that paradigm in your head, then,
hey, the emperor, he's this secular authority and he's coming in here to meddle in the
church's business, right, which he shouldn't be involved in because he's the secular authority.
Right. But of course, 325, we don't have any of those concepts yet. Again.
Yeah, I mean, we've.
But also, you literally just stopped having him for who is the chief priest.
Yes.
He's the first one to do it this way, even, to separate it this much.
So, so this idea has not has not developed yet.
But if we look at why St. Constantine says he called the council,
he called the council because he wanted to preserve the peace of the empire,
the piece and you
of the empire. Not because he was dabbling in theology, not because he wanted to weigh in on one
side or the other, not because he wanted an imperial church that would do his bidding, right? It was
because there was this theological issue that it seems like he didn't entirely understand at the
time that was deeply troubling the empire causing
civil discord, strife, lack of unity,
and his job as the emperor remember justice,
everything in the right place,
everything functioning properly, everything good,
he's concerned about this.
And so when you look at the canons of the council,
you see the canons are aimed at the communal life
of the church and thereby the communal life of the empire.
Yeah.
Right, and so this falls under his concern.
Right.
You
said, it is the bishops who decide the issues. He calls the bishop together to decide these
issues to preserve the peace and unity of the empire.
As we mentioned a couple times now, St. Constitutes theology, his own personal theology seems
like he was probably some kind of semi-Aryan, not a seminarian, not all seminarians or semi-Aryans.
Samar. Samar, yeah. So it's hard to totally tell. A lot of the case, a lot of times you'll
see people very confidently saying that he was a semi-arion. But the people, the main
reason they're saying that so confidently is that they're thinking of like UCBS of
Nicomedia and UCB as a cesarea who were semi-areans who were in his inner circle.
Yeah, and wasn't it, wasn't Nikamidia who baptized him?
Is that right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Nikamidia was sort of, the Bishop of Nikamidia
was sort of the imperial chaplain for a while.
So there's an element of guilt by association there.
Now, I'm not saying he wasn't, right?
But I'm saying we don't know, right?
We don't have, again,
We don't.
of access to his inner thoughts and feelings. But you know, he probably was somewhere in
that range because these are the guys he's hanging around with. And right, as I mentioned
before, he's trying to find some way to mediate this dispute. Right? He's not just following
on the nice inside and saying, areas you're no good, you're a heretic, he's still trying
to reconcile things for the rest of areas' life.
Now we do have the clue.
The closest thing we do have to a sort of direct window into his theological thinking is he actually delivered what is commonly titled the oration to the assembly of the saints.
Okay.
And you can look that up online.
There's five or six different public domain translations of it. It's all over the place.
There's lots of really interesting things there that again are very confirmatory.
toward the idea that this guy is at least trying to figure out how to be a Christian, right?
It'd be the emperor.
But you know, it's not long enough, it's detailed enough, it's not like him presenting a systematic
theology either where he could figure out what he believed on all these different issues.
But the key elements is speaking from a very Roman perspective in the sense that he sees
cry
is sort of the one who has delivered the Roman world, the Gentile Roman world from idolatry.
So there's a lot of
distinction made there, idolatry as an evil. The pagan worship is an evil over against. Christ is the
logos, right, bringing true knowledge of God, right, over against idolatry. But he gets into
that's a new ACS card.
of a nuanced critique of Plato in there. He talks about a number of different things and
he ends up sort of the last part of it is he's taking these ancient Roman pagan text,
he says, are from the sibling books, hard to tell if that's true. Because the sibling
books were kept secret and stuff. So I'm sure he thought they were from the sibling books
but whether they actually were or not is tricky.
We've talked about those before in the show.
But which he interprets as being prophecies of Christ that were given to the Roman civilization
to prepare them for the coming of the gospel.
Yeah.
So that's also, it's sort of a fascinating document.
Like I said, it's not a system of theology, you're not going to figure out whether he's
a heretic or not from it.
Then this case but again it gives for their answer this guy's at least
trying to think and function as a Christian and what does now?
Now that Christ had quite literally kind of appeared in his life, right now. How do I need to reorient things?
So I mentioned that aside from the hey, he didn't kill all the pagans, so he must not have been a Christian. The other big argument is and this is actually
this has a little more teeth to it is
is the fact that after his conversion he would
manipulated politically into murdering his wife and his son. Which is bad. That's bad. Yes.
Those are horrible sins, right? Horrible crimes. So we have to remember, though, that saints are saints
based on how they end up, not based on having been like perfect their whole life.
So, you know, St. Paul tells us he's responsible for a bunch of murders.
David was responsible for a murder.
People are responsible for murders.
That's not to say, oh, don't worry about it, right?
That is a grievous sin.
So then what you have to look for in his life are signs of repentance.
Right.
Um, they're forget to talk about him as a saint.
And so that brings us to his baptism.
Yes. And Legendarily goes on his deathbed, right?
So little of a Christian he waited until almost he was dead.
Yes, yeah. That's the one of the wraps he gets.
So that's not entirely true.
So people will...
also, they'll generalize past.
They just say, constitute himself and say, oh, well,
everybody, right?
Everybody got baptized on their deathbed, because they
thought there was no forgiveness of sins after baptism.
Yeah.
A lot of that is semi-imaginary.
I'm not saying no one did that.
Right, but with St. Constantine in particular, we know he wasn't doing that because St. Constantine,
near the end of his life was preparing to begin an Eastern military campaign,
meaning he was going after the Persians. And this is a whole subtopic that
this episode is going to be a long one, but are going to have to be this long.
get in relations between him and the person empire but there was an
There were a lot of changes between him and the Persians and there were issues with Persian,
the Persian Empire's persecution of Christians.
There were a couple of Persian bishops who were at the Council of Naisia.
It was a whole thing.
So he was going to begin this campaign in the East and his plan was that on his way to
the East to begin to lead this military campaign, he was going to stop off to be baptized in
the Jordan.
Yeah, he wanted it where Jesus was baptized.
Yeah.
And the then bishop of Alia, Capitolina, formerly noticed Jerusalem, was going to be one of
the participants who were spaptizing him.
It was going to be a big thing.
So he had this all planned, and then he got gravely ill.
And so that campaign, at least under him, never happened.
We won't talk about Julian, the apostate, his Eastern campaign and what happened there.
But, so that campaign never happened.
And so he ended up, because he was sick, they baptized him where he was, right?
And that ended up being his deathbed, right?
But that is because he got sick before the planned baptism.
and after...
he received that what sort of an emergency baptism, he refused to put back on the Imperial
Garb. And refused to issue any more laws. He would only wear his white baptismal robe.
And so he spent his last days in repentance.
So...
All of this stuff goes into the understanding of him as St. Constantine.
Right.
And, yes, his life is very different than that of St. Seraphim of Sarov.
Right? Or any number of other saints, right?
But the saints live different lives.
Yeah, right.
St. Constitutes a little more Old Testament saint, maybe.
Then he's definitely not a monastic saint, right?
That's...
But, yeah, yeah.
So, through all of this, through how he conducts himself, right?
Because again, he's figuring this out.
How does one be a Christian Roman Emperor?
Right?
How does one go from being the
at least semi-divine, possessed by a genius, right?
semi-divine king and high priest of the Roman state
to being a Christian emperor,
seeding spiritual authority to other people, right?
He's figuring out how to do this in his own life.
But what he sort of figures out
is the beginning of sort of the template,
sort of the pattern.
For what a Byzantine emperor,
what is our later is supposed.
to be like in how they're supposed to function.
Right, vis-à-vis the church.
And so people may have heard the term symphonia,
speaking with the same voice
that's used to describe the Byzantine emperor,
the correct role between the patriarch and the emperor.
And again, sometimes we read into that,
our idea of the separation of church and state
even our idea of like sacred and secular spheres.
years that are two different things.
And that's not really the distinction between the two
and their authority.
So the actual distinction is, for one thing, as we mentioned,
the emperor cannot perform sacraments.
Including, as we mentioned with the caller,
he's not supposed to perform his own coronation.
He can't celebrate the Eucharist, he can't do any of those things.
That is not an authority that he has.
We talked about what the monarch's job is in the first half, from the Scriptures.
Establishing and maintaining justice, right, and the proper functioning of communal life.
Those are the authority serving as the icon of Christ.
in both senses, right? So he has a ministry, he has a type of ministry, but it is not the same as
the priestly ministry, right? And so they function together in symphony, they are to function together
in symphony in the same sense that a bishop and a priest and a deacon are supposed to function together
in symphony, right? Those three have different ministries, but they should all be functioning
together on the same page and speaking with the same voice, we're just adding in the
tomorrow.
who has this other separate ministry, right, but which should be acting in concert,
pun kind of intended with the others, right? And so now when we move into the
third half, we will get into the sort of nitty gritty, we'll get to the actual
topic and talk about the actual coordination of the emperor, and then after that
sort of very
practical side will talk a little more about the way in which coming out of the New Testament,
how all of this that we've been talking about informs our understanding of things like
government and politics and those kind of things. So, it sure will be super non-controversial with
everyone. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, we will take a short break and we'll be right back with more
Lord of Spirits. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steve
Even the young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord
of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient faith publishing is pleased to announce a new release that is part history, part theology,
and part devotional.
the story of Jesus. A history of...
theology of Christ explores the complete life and teachings of our Lord, from before
his conception in Mary's womb until his ascension. Revealed 20th century Egyptian elder and
scholar Matthew the poor, wrote many volumes on the subject of Christ's significance, life,
and teachings. Which translator James Helmi has distilled into one highly readable book that will
will make a valuable addition to every Christian's library.
The story of Chief-
Jesus is now available in paperback and ebook at store.ancientfake.com.
That's store.ancientfake.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody. It's the third...
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
And we're talking about the making of kings.
This continues our series on sacraments.
This is sacrament number eight.
Where will we end?
I don't know.
I really don't know.
But not here.
Not now.
So all right.
Without ever knowing the way.
Anyway, not where were they going?
Yeah, yes.
Yes, well, we'll be talking now about someone,
the road that he walks on is not paved in gold,
but he could have made that happen if he wanted to.
Rich and awful guy.
So, right, so in doing some of the research for this show,
we came across a really interesting text,
which is called Russian Travelers to Constantinople
in the 14th and 15th centuries.
Which, I mean, every kid should have this on his shelf
and don't yours, you know, most people,
Yeah.
Absolutely. We all read this in middle school, right?
It's not as exciting as Goleverse travels.
I must say.
That is true.
So more pertinent to the life of the church.
The Goleverse travel.
A little bit more.
Yeah.
So the editor is George P. Majeska.
I don't know if it's Majeska or Majeska,
but I want it to be Majeska.
And so the book is actually a collection of...
Like it says on the link.
you know, Russian travelers to Constantinople in the 14th and 15th centuries.
And one of the travelers that he quotes, he actually includes the source material and then there's commentary and stuff.
Is a text called the Journey of Ignatius of Smolensk. And this is from the late 14th century.
So this is getting towards the end of the Eastern Roman aka Byzantine Empire.
Is when Ignatius of Smolensk makes his visit to Constantinople.
One of the fun things about these travelers...
is that they go on these trips and then they write down the stuff that they saw.
Often they are the only people writing these texts that we have
because sometimes the people who are living there don't ever bother writing it down
because like, well, everybody knows what happens or whatever.
So anyways...
Right.
So this...
We should be clear.
Right. We just talked about saying Constantine.
So he's the beginning of this.
So he didn't have a Christian coronation.
because he sort of became emperor, by inheritance and then conquest.
This is like a thousand years later now, more than a thousand years later.
This is the other end of the Byzantine emperor.
So this is sort of the full flowering in terms of the right of coronation, in terms of
this sacramental coronation of the emperor.
And so this one, so he witnesses the coronation.
of manuals to the second paleologos who is not the the ultimate emperor meaning the last he's
not the penultimate emperor meaning next last he is the anti-pinaltimate emperor next next
next you just wanted to use that word that's all that was I do not get to use that word every day
well you need to you need to study Greek more because then then you know because you define where
you put the...
accent mark, whether it's on the anti-pennelt or the anti-pennelt.
Yeah, yeah. So, yeah, so he's number three from the end and he rains from 1391 to 1425.
So, most of this is from Ignatius of Smolensk, but there are some other details from other
sources included in this. So, this is a rough outline of what his coronation actually would
of look like. So before they start the coordination proper.
or Stone Masons, walk up to the emperor and they show him chunks of marble.
I'm not kidding about this.
They show him chunks of marble and they say to him, what sort of tomb will your majesty
order for himself?
The idea being like, you're going to die.
So as he's about to be crowned the most powerful guy in the world, you're going to die.
Right.
So that as Deuteronomy says, his heart will not exalt himself above his brethren.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so then there's this idea then there's prayers that are said that he's going to establish a righteous empire
Right, just empire that you have establishing justice. Yeah, right
So the patriarch of Constance Noble and other clergy then they come out of the altar and they go up to the Ombo
Which is that in most churches now is the space right kind of right in front of
the the Holy Doors
They go to the Ombo and they invite the Emperor to join join them, right?
So he comes up and the patriarch reads a
prayer for the success of the Emperor's reign, and then he chants holy three times, holy, holy, holy.
And so that sort of connects it, right, with the divine counsel, where we hear the Thrice Holy
hymn. The people then, they start chanting the Holy over and over again. And while they do that,
the patriarch anoints the head of the Emperor with chryism in the form of a cross.
plus. And then
So then after that happens, the crown of the emperor
is brought out from the sanctuary, from the holy place,
or we sometimes call it the altar, by two deacons.
They bring the crown out.
And then after that, then the empress's crown
is brought out by relatives or by two unix.
I'm not sure whether it's unix around,
but there are unix.
And they then escort her to the center of the church.
So she's not up on the umbo where her husband is.
She's in the...
out of the solea ways, probably kind of roughly the center of the church, towards the front
those still. And then this is an interesting detail and I want to look this one up because
I'm not really sure what this is about. But the patriarch first puts a hood on the emperor's
head, and then he places the crown on it, and then he chants oxios three times. So I mean,
looking a little bit like an ordination in some ways.
Not quite the same.
Similar, they're clearly elements. He's yeah, he's receiving an office and a ministry. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
And then Ignatius of Smolensk says that the patriarch puts a cross in the emperor's hand. This is probably a
Scepter with a cross on top of it, right? So it's a cross Scepter and
then the the patriarch and the emperor descend from the Ambo to the Salleah, which is where the empress is, right?
and the emperor then crowns the emperor.
So you can see her, her role is quite different.
You know, she does not receive all this stuff from the patriarch, but it's her husband,
then who gives her the crown.
And then she shares it with her.
Yeah, yeah, sort of like a Presbyterra.
Yeah, there you go.
And so then the emperor then places a gold wand decorated with gems into her hand.
So it's kind of a scepter, but not quite the same thing.
And then the emperor and the empress then go back to their thrones and the deacons in tone
known act.
for the Royal Family.
God grant you many years.
And that's the order, basically as Ignatius of Simmelansk,
with some details from other sources
that this scholar has put together for us.
That's essentially the order of the coronation of an emperor
with the anti-punultimate emperor
before the fall of Consonz and Opal.
Yes, and this is during the liturgy,
if I'm correct.
Correct. Right?
Yeah. And so then
As
with many sacriots, there's sort of a culmination in the reception of the Eucharist.
Yeah, we'll talk about that in a little bit by the emperor and Empress, yeah, which
we will get to.
We'll get to that.
And people will be puzzled and dismayed, but you'll make it.
It'll be great.
We'll stay with you.
We're here for you.
We'll be ruining both sort of Sunday school and all the things that the Babushki
Yeah, guys tell you that told you yeah
So
Right, so here we have clearly expressed within the ritual right
At those connections to an ordination right that that again there's this ministry. There's this office being received by the emperor
But that is not again just something that grows out of
the practical matters of St. Constantine and the emperors thereafter. This is
something that has its root back in St. Paul, specifically in what St. Paul says
about the governing authorities, which of course in his day was the Roman Empire
and the Roman Emperor.
pagan, pagan, pagan ones, the pagan ones who were persecuting the church.
Yeah, beginning to at least who had killed Christ, right?
Romans 13 specifically verses 1 through 7.
Okay, where he talks about this.
Yeah, I'm going to read this off. Let every person be subject to the governing authorities.
For there is no authority except from God and those that exist have been instituted by God.
Therefore, whoever resists the authorities resists what God has appointed.
and those resist will incur judgment. For rulers are not a terror to good conduct, but to bad.
Would you have no fear of the one who is an authority? Then do it as good, and you will receive his approval,
for he is God's servant for your good. But if you do wrong, be afraid, for he does not bear the sword in vain.
For he is the servant of God, an avenger who carries out God's wrath on the wrong door.
Therefore, one must be in subjection, not only to avoid God's wrath, but also for the sake of conscience.
Thanks.
Because of this, you also pay taxes.
For the authorities are ministers of God
attending to this very thing.
Pay to all what is owed to them.
Taxes to whom taxes are owed.
Revenue to whom revenue is owed.
Respect to whom respect is owed.
Honor to whom honor is owed.
Right.
So you see a couple elements there.
One is we're just referring to that the civil magistrate,
Right.
In this case, the
Roman authorities are God's servants.
Yeah. And that's add that the power, including the power of the sword, which is what a Roman emperor later had Saint Paul killed with, is given to them by God.
And so we see this element, that's the one side of the rule
as icon and as minister and then St. Paul goes to the other side, right, which is that
veneration and honor, right, and obedience, which is owed to the other way again, not based
on the goodness or anything, any other qualities of the particular ruler, but the fact that
they are the person who is in this position of God given authority.
And this mostly a lot of the majority, I wish all Orthodox people had this understanding
with clergy, right, that the respect that we pay to a bishop or to a priest or a deacon
right, is not based on their personal qualities, but based on
on the office they've received from God that God is the person who will judge them and
deal with them regarding how they've used that office and authority they've been granted.
Say Paul is saying the same kind of thing is true of the governmental authorities because
they also have this office from God and this responsibility from God.
And this is, say Paul's position that he takes here is over against...
the increasingly popular array of Jewish positions at this time toward the Roman government
that generally get categorized as zealotry.
St. Paul has his own period of zealotry against the church, right?
But it's not the quote-unquote political zealotry that for example is going to lead to the Jewish
revolts that are going to get Jerusalem destroyed.
There are, of course, three Jewish revolts, but much like the original Matrix trilogy,
everybody only wants to talk about the first one, and they get worse as they go.
But so, and this is so common, we see this reflected, right, two of Christ's disciples,
say, Simon the Zealot, obviously he's labeled as a zealot, but this is also actually what
Eschariat.
It seems to mean in reference to Judas.
He was one of the secari who were an extremely militant zealot group that literally spent
their time assassinating Roman officials.
Yeah, look this up people.
They carried around deck.
So they were kind of ready at any time to stick it in some guys back.
But they got the opportunity to kill a Roman, they took it.
Yeah.
Yeah, so Judas might have been one of these people.
Yeah, it seems like, seems most likely that that's what that's referring to.
Man.
So this position is crazy popular.
This is why Christ gets asked whether it's lawful to pay taxes to Caesar.
Right?
Because there are, from extreme militancy, murderous militancy all the way to people who become tax collectors who are complete class.
collectors who are complete.
collaborators, right?
This range of positions within occupied Judea and Galilee at this time.
And St. Paul takes the position we outlined.
And for St. Paul, that doesn't mean just like slave-ish obedience, right?
So when the Roman authority says no more preaching the gospel, he's still going to preach the gospel.
Yeah, right.
You have to be God rather than man.
Right. But what it does mean, his position does mean is that then he will voluntarily accept
the consequences of that. Yeah, if you could ultimately. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, if you're
going to resist the government, you don't complain. You accept whatever happens to you.
Right. And so when that means he gets executed, he goes to his execution and becomes a martyr.
Right. Right. He doesn't try to get people to break him out.
he doesn't, right? So I think in part this position that St. Paul takes is influenced by his past.
He was born and spent his early years in Tarsus and at one point after his conversion, not
immediately after when he went to Orambia, but after, went back to Tarsus for a period of time,
probably at least a couple of years. And Tarsis is an interesting
city and community. We won't spend too much time on it right now. But what's primarily
interesting about it in this regard is that during the whole contest, so Tarsus is kind
of in the crook where Asia Minor, what's now Turkey, meets the Levant, right? Like what's
now Lebanon, right? Like in the crook there, and it's at the mouth of a river. So it's
kind of centrally located there and became this strategic position.
So like...
Antony and Cleopatra mustered their troops there for the Battle of Actium, for example.
But in this regard, what's important is during the rivalry between Caesar and Pompey,
Tarsus and its surroundings, including its very large Jewish community,
were deeply loyal to Julius Caesar.
And when they did that, Caesar took notice of it.
And he made Tarsus a free city, which gave them a bunch of tax exemptions and other things.
And he issued a mass grant of citizenship, not only to the officials in the city itself,
but also to the prominent members of the large Jewish community.
community who were his supporters in the area. This is how St. Paul ended up being a Roman citizen.
He tells when he's arrested in Jerusalem in in Acts, he tells the Sachery and that he received
his citizenship by birth, which means likely his grandfather based on the timing was one of these
Jews at the time who received Roman citizenship from Caesar. And then you're able to give that to
to your descendants.
And the prominence of the support from this Jewish community is what led to the toleration
of Judaism, not only in the area, but ultimately in the whole Roman Empire.
Wow.
This is why Jews were relatively...
I mean, there were always issues.
Caligula was crazy.
Tried to put a statue of himself in the Temple of Jerusalem, right?
There were things, right.
on the whole
and Claudius expeling the Jews from Rome.
But on the whole,
Jewish communities scattered around the Roman Empire
could generally exempt from having to engage
in pagan sacrifice, from having to do these things.
They were able to sort of live out their own lives
within the larger community, keeping Torah, right.
But so that's the way of life that St. Paul experienced
as a very young man, and then again later in life.
So
So he had seen an example.
I think this colored his view of the Gentiles
and the Romans in general too.
He had seen that they were not entirely unreasonable,
they were not animals.
He had seen that if one was willing to give honor
and respect to authority, not 100%,
but a lot of the time, you would be allowed to,
as he says, the pastoral epistles
live a quiet and peaceful life in godliness and sanctity,
Right.
You pay your taxes, you know, you meet your obligations, you show the respect that these people deserve and they basically leave you alone.
Right. And so that seems to have colored his position because that's sort of the position he takes for Christians of how Christians should try to live in this pagan world.
Right. Is the same kind of thing. Give respect to who it's due. Pay your taxes. Right. Do good in your community.
Right, and, and uh...
good things will, will follow or at least they'll mostly leave you alone, right?
But St. Paul also had a game plan. This is also very clear, both in acts and in his epistles.
And the culmination of that game plan, the end game of it, was that he wanted to
preach the gospel to and convert the emperor.
Yeah, he's always trying to get there.
Yeah, trying to get to Rome and when he gets arrested, he's like, well, I'll appeal my way there, right?
Yeah.
Here's my chance.
And we know while he's at her house arrest, you know, ultimately he's in Rome.
He's talking to, he's got members of Caesar's household and stuff who he's talking to.
Right. He's trying to get that audience. He's trying to bring the emperor to Christ.
Right.
And for part of that time that he's thinking that you've got emperors like Caligula and Nero, right?
So these aren't like nice people or sane people
He's essentially trying to convert the Antichrist to Christianity, right?
Like he strikes a
Wow
This guy was proclaimed himself a God, right? This guy was
And he's gonna try and get him to become a Christian. So
But what happens with St. Constantine when he converts is St. Paul's plan coming to fruition.
This is again not this radical thing that the apostles never could have conceived of.
They very much could conceive of it.
Maybe not of everything that would happen afterwards, but they could conceive of a world in which
That could happen.
happen and that if that happened, how much of the world would then become Christian?
And how would the world change and how would idolatry cease, right?
So this is very much in tune with the first century gospel.
So there's not this great disjunction, right, that almost all of those conspiracy theories
and a bunch of others we didn't mention are based on.
the Christian.
was going in this one direction and then Constantine comes and derails it takes it in this other direction.
This was the direction. Yeah. Now, so now all that said, all that said, as the big Leno out there,
yes, I know out there there's a whole bunch of folks who identify as monarchists who got super
excited that we're going to be talking about state Constantine and the coordination of the emperor.
Okay, we gotta talk guys.
up. You may have noticed there aren't actually really any more monarchies. Not in the sense
we've been talking about anymore in our world today. Yeah, I mean, there's a handful like,
you know, like Brunei and Oman, you know, yeah, like these are not even that monarchs. Right,
They're not Christian monarch and well so you've got I won't have you got
countries who still have royal families as sort of figureheads.
Right. Um, that's not to say they don't have certain social and cultural
roles and responsibilities, but just in the sense that they're not actually
governing the state, right? That's right. So soon to be, I don't know, is he
soon to be King Charles the third or is he King Charles is there? I don't know.
It's partated like 15 times. Yeah. He is King Charles. The crowning doesn't
happen until sometime in May, if I remember correctly.
Okay.
Or the current king of the Netherlands,
who's staying willom almost all the other ones.
That's right.
It works, it works.
You have people who are essentially dictators
like some of those people you just mentioned.
Where there's no sacramental character
to what they're doing.
Right, right, there's no,
there's no, you know,
there's a big difference between Stalin and the Tsar.
Right.
Both of them in a certain sense had absolute power, but not really doing the same thing, right?
Even a bad czar was doing a fundamentally different thing.
He was just doing it badly.
Or very common now, especially the West, is you have councils with no king.
and parliaments and the current situation.
situation in almost all of these places is the result of a series of refolds and revolutions most of them bloody
and and violent
Right and you know, so it's not that we sort of have peacefully evolved to a higher place than monarchy. It's
You know blood so history of kings getting murdered and that sort of thing
Um, and, uh,
And again, I hate to tell everybody, but in the real world, it's not coming back in our
lifetime.
But we're not going to end on a depressing note like that.
Yeah.
We're not going to end on a depressing note like that.
So what?
Right.
I'm sorry.
We don't have monarchy. We definitely don't have a sacramentally coordinated emperor or king.
Who's the actual head of state, the functioning head of state?
So, can we just scrap this episode? Why did we bother doing it? It's just a historical curiosity, right?
for nerds. No, and yes, I know.
So I know that in like 38,000 years we'll have a God Emperor, but I won't be around then.
That'll be half, you know, gigantic worm or whatever.
So I was daused anyway.
Wrong franchise.
I just did.
So but we do still have a civil magistrate.
Right.
still have people.
in various governmental positions of authority,
what can we take from this and apply it to them?
And so we're going to start at a place,
and I want to be clear before we start at this place,
that we're about to talk about how the Emperor
and the Empress received the Eucharist.
We are not saying that your local government officials
should receive the Eucharist this way with their wives or husbands.
even if they're Orthodox.
Just to be clear, even if they're Orthodox,
we're not saying you should do this,
but we're going to look at this and then we're going to take some lessons from this.
Yes. Okay.
So, as we mentioned, right,
the sort of the culmination of that service that Father Andrew read through described
is when they received the Eucharist.
Yeah.
So, the way that this works is
during the Tarroubic hymn in the divine liturgy.
So you know this is when the clerk
and the ultra-servers are about to make the procession of the, you know,
of the unconsecrated bread and wine into the sanctuary.
So during the truba kim, the emperor enters into the sanctuary through the holy doors,
aka the royal doors, although this is one of my little bugaboo's, those are not the royal doors.
World Doys are in the back of the church.
just walk through them. That was pretty, that's pretty normal.
That's true, it's true, but anyway, but yeah, so.
Two shay. Two shay.
Yeah, he enters into the doors that are at the center of the kind of stasis.
So he's, you know, walking straight up to the altar.
And his wife, she enters through one of the deacon's doors.
The south. So she walks right up in the middle.
When he goes to enter. Yeah, yeah.
This is a bit takes across the country.
That's right as people just so ceremonial entrance of the Empress into the Holy
Yes, yes behind the altar and you know who got really mad about this and it started all their problems
Nestorius
Second time he's come up
Wow, he got mad about the Empress coming coming and receiving communion in this actuary
And she defended herself by saying, well, the Theotokos entered into the
temple. Mike drop. But please, I went into the Holy of Holies. And the story is rather
than just saying to Shay said, you should call it theotokos, all what south from there.
Yes. So when they go in, when they go in, the emperor gets a little felonian put on him.
So all you young men in the Slavic traditions when you become readers.
You're being vested like the emperor for like a hot minute.
But yes, the emperor gets a little fallonian.
Do not exalt your hearts above your brothers.
Indeed, yes, it's right.
And they hand him a sensor.
The emperor stands at the altar, next to the altar, and he senses while the clergy
Bring the bread and the wine into the old.
So he's sensing as a great entrance. Yeah, at the great entrance. Yep. Yep. And so then
fast forward a bit into in the liturgy when it's time for communion. The emperor,
he receives the Eucharist from the patriarch. Notice he does not go get it himself.
He receives it from the patriarch and he communes along with all the clergy. So he communes at
the altar with the clergy.
And then the Empress is communed within the sanctuary.
So she's there, she's inside the Holy Place, but she's not like at the altar with the
clergy, but she's communed within.
And so that's how the Empress, at least at this later Byzantine period, received Holy
Communion.
Right.
And again, we're not saying that you should do this with your local mayor and his wife
or her husband.
Right.
Right, what does this once again emphasize? Right, that this is an office and a ministry. Right.
That is the key element that this is emphasizing. Right, they're not communing as laity.
They're communing as people with offices from God within the church. And so, even though, again,
we do not communicate our
civil magistrates this way.
This idea that the authority that the civil magistrate has, whether he's the mayor, whether he's the tax assessor, whether he's the president of the United States, whether he's the prime minister,
is given to them by God.
They are in a sense a minister of God
with responsibilities
Right to promulgate again not their own will
but the law and commandments of God and to serve as image in those two senses. Right?
That they are to image the rule of Christ over the earth, right? By how they conduct
their office and they are honored, they are venerated by us, right? As those who have
been given the authority to do that, we pay them the respect they are due even
when they're lousy.
Yeah, right. You know, again, see David and Saul. Yeah, exactly. Right.
So, right, even if Joe Biden comes to kill me, I will say, why are you coming here to murder me,
Mr. President? Don't you have better things to do? Right. But meanwhile, welcome to Louisiana,
I would like some. Yeah. So now that said right.
That sort of gives us at least a little flavor of our relevance for all this.
Even if we aren't really currently and, as I said, within our lifetimes, we're not going to really practice this sacrament, this mystery of the church.
There's still an issue.
And this issue I want to at least point out because this is something
the church has not done yet. And I think part of the reason the church hasn't done this yet
is that the Orthodox church, so it's only been a little over a hundred years since
Russia had an emperor. Yeah. And they were under Communism for most of that.
that, that swaths.
of the Orthodox Church are under Islamic governments.
Right?
So the Orthodox Church does not have a long history
of living in liberal democracies.
Right?
This is a relatively recent thing for us.
And since the fall of Constantinople,
modernity rising has generally been greeted
by kind of apocalypticism,
a lot of orthodox sources, right?
So there hasn't been a lot of attention given to how do we function long-term in this new
structuring of the world because the fact that we have this new structuring of the world
was taken to be a clear sign that it was about to end.
Well, yeah, assuming it doesn't end in my lifetime, which of course it could, right?
We have to figure out how to function.
And there's that...
Living in a democratic, I would say a democracy, really, it's a democratic system, right?
Republican system, whatever, you know, we want to strictly call it.
The kind of democratic system presents a fundamental puzzle to Christian ethics and Christian
social ethics that we haven't really paid much attention to.
Yes, seriously.
For reasons.
Working through it.
described, right? And what do I mean by?
that. Well, in a sense, right, if you're voting on things, right, if you're, in some cases,
directly more often indirectly in a sort of representative sense, right, voting on issues
that that means every person is a magistrate of sorts. So we also be being communed up inside
the old no what not what we're saying yeah
But it's sort of everyone is and no one is, right?
But clearly there's a fundamental difference between me and the president of the United States
or the prime minister of the UK in terms of functioning as a magistrate even though like their
ballot propositions of Louisiana that I can vote on.
And if they win the vote, they go into force of law.
So that's a different structure, right?
And the whole structure of rights.
Right, so let me give an example.
There's a whole question, right?
Should a Christian vote?
People come down on different sides of this.
Right, like, should I vote at all?
Right, if the available candidates
who theoretically could win the election
are all problematic,
Should I not? Should I not vote? What if that's always kind of true? Should I just never vote?
Or is there some kind of responsibility?
Does that being a magistrate of a sort mean that I have a responsibility to exercise that power which would of course have come from God and therefore do I by should I vote it do I have a a a duty?
To go and vote and exercise that power in some sense, right?
This is not something that has been fully thought through in terms of the
Orthodox tradition. And part of the reason for that is like when the United States government
was found, it was deliberately designed after the pre-Christian Roman Republic.
Right. And then if we do conclude that you either should or at least can or it's indifferent
for you to vote. Theological approach, how do you vote?
Yeah, because because like you know you vote for a candidate or you know maybe you can vote for much more narrowly like a referendum or proposition or something like that.
Or a party or depending on your system.
Yeah.
Right. And maybe you can endorse some of the things that'll happen as result could happen as a result of their vote.
And some things that you cannot endorse or again...
You know, there's the problem of what if you vote for someone and then they do something other than what they said they were going to do.
Are you responsible for that? Because you helped put them in power.
Right? So, I mean, it's complicated from a Christian ethical point of view.
At least in most, for most of the people listening to this, maybe not all, but for most of the people listening to this,
There's not somebody or a party you could go-
vote for whose platform is Orthodox Christianity.
Yeah, no.
No.
Right.
So this is a whole complex series of issues, right?
That we still need to wrestle with and still need to sort out.
But we can take an overall approach.
So within, for example, the Christianized
Roman Empire, the Christian Roman Empire, what did clergy and people do, especially a
good example is when they had bad empires, right, when they had what under what are the
bad ones, right? And what you see is, you see a veneration of the office, you see honor
and respect being given, you see the pattern by Saint Paul, and then you see the clergy
and the church.
There's a whole, and even the laity, then exhorting those people who find themselves in power
to govern rightly, to govern righteously, to govern with justice.
And that approach, at least, is one that we can directly take regardless of our system
of government.
Right.
That we can both be respectful of the authorities, keep the laws up to and until they conflict
with God's Law and to continue to exhort those who are in
power to utilize the responsibilities they've invested with the authority and power they've
invested with by God in the manner that God has called them to use it. All right, well, we're here
at the end. So I have so many thoughts about this stuff that we've been talking about in terms of
of where you could kind of go with this.
I think that...
One of the biggest temptations, I think particularly for people who convert to the Orthodox
Christian faith and discover, at least even some piece of all the stuff we've just been
talking about with regards to emperors and kings and stuff, is to, I really want that.
Wow, it looks great.
It's so glorious and shiny, you know, despite the fact that, of course, the vast majority
of even Orthodox Christian monarchs were not great.
you know and sometimes people pine for monarchy and it's like well you know
number one that's not gonna happen like you just said but but also like most
of us most people living under a monarchy are not the important people most
people are living way down at the bottom right and you know that can be for
salvation. But I think that
the vast majority of Orthodox Christians or any Christians or whoever is listening to this
are not pining for monarchy.
You know, are not monarchists or not ideologues along these lines.
Most are probably just asking the question of like, well, how am I supposed to understand
all this and how am I supposed to make sense of the fact that largely speaking most of these
monarchs have not been good people or even decent people.
in a lot of cases.
What are you supposed to do with that?
You know, I think one of the things that, as I've studied history over the course of
my life that I've discovered, and I think particularly in the last several years as I've
made a deep study of some particular times of places of history, is that you kind of
have two choices of where you can land in terms of being a Christian and reading this kind
of stuff and trying to understand it.
One is that you can become very cynical.
And certainly people do, right?
That often there's a pretty bad track record.
And I mean, you don't even have to just look at kings and queens and emperors and emperors
as you can even just look at clergy.
There's often a pretty bad track record.
So that's one way you can become cynical.
You can say it's all just bonk or forget it.
I've had enough.
But the other way is the way that I prefer and the one that I think is
actually the Christian way, honestly, which is to look at all of it with hope. Hope.
And our hope is in the King of Kings.
Right? The scripture at the same time that it says, put not your trust in princes or in sons of men,
also says all these things about good kingship. But it's not to say that even David
is the end, is, you know, the point at which all of this has become what it's supposed to be.
Because not even he, who's man after God's own heart, not even he was the one that all kingship was pointing towards. That's Christ.
Christ is the one.
And so our hope is not a hope in any particular government system.
It's not a hope in the rise of a
Pious, saintly, holy Orthodox.
emperor. That's that's not what it is. And honestly, I mean, I had this thought a number
of times when we were preparing for this episode, which is, you know, let's imagine here in America
that there's a king. What kind of king would America generate? Probably most of us would
not want to live under that king, not great. So, you know, that aside though, the point of
all this is the point of
is Christ. And so what do you do in the meantime? I think one of the things that you discover,
especially as you study Church history in particular, is that while there is the grand game of power
and borders and territories and riches and all this kind of stuff, while that is always going on
in this life. There is a more important story that is also going on.
It's not that these two stories have nothing to do with each other.
They have everything to do with each other.
But it is that the story of the saints who are sort of the through line of all of this,
that is going to be revealed at the end of time as the story of those who are in a sense
really ruling.
Right?
It's the saints who, as the scripture says, judge angels to whom the world to come is
subjected.
They're the ones co-raining with Christ, and they show us what that looks like by doing
it.
What does it look like for the saints to reign in glory?
It looks like what they're doing for us right now.
They are intercessors for us before the throne of God.
They also help to minister and to manage this creation in concert with God.
And the more that you look at, even the very, very dark chapters of history, I think the
more, and if you look at it really, really honestly and seek out the face of Christ in
this, then you will see that there's always hope.
Sometimes it feels kind of buried, but there is always hope.
There's always hope.
And if we look at history and if we look at questions of…
kingship and monarchy and government with triumphalism, then it's going to go very dark.
It's going to get super dark because that's really about power.
But if we look at it with hope, then we're looking for Christ because He is our hope.
He is the hope of the hopeless, right, the savior of the stormtossed.
And I think that's the way that many of us, especially at this point right now in American
history in particular. Again.
I know that lots of our listeners are not Americans, but most of y'all are.
And certainly in other parts of the world too, so even if you're not American, that it
can feel pretty hopeless.
It can feel pretty storm tossed.
There's a lot of nutty stuff going on, dangerous stuff, despairing stuff, depressing stuff.
And yet we always have our hope in Christ.
Always, always.
Above all other people, Christians should be joyful.
our joy is possible because...
Christ is King. He also has sub-Kings under him and in his much as our government officials are
showing that as icons, thank God, we still need to honor them and respect them and obey them
in as much as they don't tell us to disobey God. But ultimately it's the saints who are really
those co-rainers with Christ and everything points finally to him.
Bob Steven.
So there's a sort of unique paradox in contemporary life, which is that at the same time everything
is hyper-political and everything is apolitical.
And who would I mean by that?
We may be more aware of the hyperpolitical side.
All of a sudden where you buy a chicken sandwich and who gets cast as the little mermaid is a political act of some sort.
Everything, every movie that comes out, every TV show that comes out, every announcement of anything, any opinion, any performance, any song, any anything
is folded into a weird part.
partisan politics thing.
At the same time, though, really things are completely apolitical because none of that
continued churn of lining up on either side of literally everything.
Ever produces any change in the world.
has any kind of actual effect on anyone's real life?
And it turns through so quickly that we can't even remember
half of these things, right?
Like, you know, the profound angst over,
like the Captain Marvel movie.
Anybody remember that?
This was something we needed to argue about
before anybody even saw it.
Now nobody cares.
And on the A political side, you know.
When you look at people's social media, everybody sort of identifies as things.
There are all of these sort of political labels.
Some of the folks who got really excited about this episode might label themselves monarchists.
You got people out there who are an arco-capitalist.
You got people out there who are an arco-primitivist, who dream of living in the woods with a rock
or something.
You've got people like me who are radical anti-centress.
You've got Marxist, Leninist, Maoist, tankies.
You've got all these people who put all these labels on themselves and sort of performatively
issue these statements on social media as their quote unquote political identity, but it's
just sort of an identity.
Sort of like being a joker, a stoner, a goth in high school.
You put this thing on yourself or if you've decided to identify them, you're going to
with more mainstream politics, right?
You repost things and you line up on either side of everything.
But none of that has anything to do with what politics actually is.
If you go back to, as is my want, say Aristotle's politics, right?
Politics is just the ethics of life and community together.
And we may not be able to recreate.
in our present day the kind of biblical and traditional model that we described in today's episode.
But we can certainly exercise Christian, I don't want to say morality, but Christian ethics, right?
A Christian way of life, a Christian way of being in the world.
You'd follow the teachings of the Orthodox Church and the way of life that the Orthodox Church
represents.
in community with each other.
The biggest barrier to that right now
is not that the Christian ethic is so hard to follow,
or not that we don't love and care about the other people who go to our church.
It's that we aren't actually living communal lives at all.
We're all isolated, signaling our respective stances on things
on things performatively unsurundable.
social media. We're all sort of consuming media and or chicken sandwiches to indicate
where we stand on things and that we're a good person and not one of those bad people.
And we're not engaging with each other. But there's also nothing stopping us from doing
that in the sense that no one is going to physically
Halt us from going down to the church to staying there and talking to people
to helping people there who need help visiting with each other in each other's
houses spending time together addressing issues in that community addressing
issues in the broader community around us. I'm not talking about whole nations
I'm not even necessarily talking about whole cities it might just be neighborhoods
It might just be, hey, you know what, a lot of trash gets left.
on our street. Why don't we go out and pick it up together and spend time together doing that?
And maybe while we're out there, we'll actually meet some of the other people who live next door to
us and who live in our area who we've never talked to and we don't know their names. And maybe when
we talk to them and they talk to us, maybe they might become part of our community and our church
community. And maybe we can start to transform this thing. And maybe that's what politics actually is.
At least what Christian poet.
what a big fix actually is.
And those things can start small in a few places.
They can actually grow very quickly.
Places can be transformed very quickly.
And before you know it, the world we live in,
maybe not the world out there, maybe not the world that's funneled to us by cable news
and through the internet and over social media.
But the world we actually...
live in once we go out and start living there in community can be very transformed and very different.
And we can feel very different about it and about our lives. And we can feel a sense of connection
that we've lost. And even if we don't have a single human king to represent Christ to us in
in terms of the civil authority.
There are all kinds of people in our community.
who have leadership qualities, who have expertise in different areas, who can both represent
Christ and the way of life in Christ to us and who are worthy of our respect in return.
So even though this is a sacrament, we've just described that, as I already said, probably
No one listening to this is going to get to participate in during our lifetimes.
The fundamental reality of it, the work of God that it represents in our communities and
our communal life, is something we can at least taste when we take seriously the fact that
we're living together and that we want the life that we live together to be one of good
order of holiness of righteousness.
Therefore of justice.
Amen.
All right, well that is our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening everyone.
If you didn't happen to call us live this time,
we'd still adhere from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsadangestianfaith.com.
You can message our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com-slash-LordOfSpirits.
and join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursday
of the month at 7pm Eastern for Pacific, even if you are the king of rock and there
is none higher.
If you're on Facebook, follow our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings
everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going
to love it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, Stroke Support.
And I'll make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the R. Even if, Sucka MCs
call you Sire.
please read WV8's The Old Stone.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you.
Thank you, God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
faith radio and I be held and I heard the voice of
many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders, and the number of
them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy
as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor
and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12